中文字幕
- --we know?
- That at 9:15, Ray Santoya was at the ATM.
中文字幕
- So the question is, what was he doing at 9:16?
- Shooting the nine-millimeter at something.
中文字幕
Maybe he saw the sniper.
- Or he was working with him.
中文字幕
- Right.
Go back one.
中文字幕
- What do you see?
- Bring his face up.
中文字幕
Full screen.
- His glasses.
中文字幕
- There's a reflection.
- That's Neuvitas baseball team.
中文字幕
That's their logo.
- And he's talking to whoever is wearing that jacket.
中文字幕
- We may have a witness.
- To both shootings.
中文字幕
This is he is CS50, and this is lecture 3, and that
is not how computer science works.
中文字幕
And indeed, by the end of today, we'll make
clear exactly what's right, what's not right about that,
中文字幕
and hopefully give you some pause any time you watch TV or movies hereafter
and notice these little things that all too many writers seem
中文字幕
to take for granted.
So recall that last time, we took a look lower level at what compiling actually
中文字幕
is.
And recall that it was a few things, these four steps of pre-processing
中文字幕
and compiling and assembling and linking,
so that when you start with their source cod,
中文字幕
that might look like this code that we have written in the past,
you first have to preprocess it, and the first step in pre-processing was
中文字幕
converting all of those processor instructions--
anything starting with a hash at the beginning-- to their equivalents.
中文字幕
So opening the files and effectively copying and pasting the contents
there so that programs and the compiler know what get_string
中文字幕
is and know what printf is.
The next step that came after that was actually
中文字幕
compiling, whereby compiling technically means taking that source
code, once it's been preprocessed, and printing and generating
中文字幕
this very cryptic-looking stuff called assembly code.
And those assembly codes or assembly instructions are really what the CPU--
中文字幕
the brain of your computer-- actually understands,
although technically the computer understands them only in the form
中文字幕
of 0's and 1's.
And so when you "assemble-- step three--
中文字幕
that assembly code, you actually get out those 0's and 1's.
But even that simplest of programs where we just prompt the user for a string
中文字幕
and then print out their name still involved a couple more files.
There was not only cs50.h and stdio.h at the top,
中文字幕
somewhere in the computer system there's probably files called cs50.c,
and in the case of stdio, printf.c, in which actually the code is
中文字幕
for those two functions, those two have to get compiled down
to 0's and 1's, and then we need to link everything together,
中文字幕
merging those 0's and 1's so that the computer has access to your code
and to printf's code and to the cs50 library's code And so forth.
中文字幕
But all of that we can just generally wrap up in the descriptor of compiling.
And so that's one of the looks we took last week.
中文字幕
And we also have introduced, last week and previously, a few tools.
And odds are, you're having as many frustrations perhaps already
中文字幕
with the p-sets as you are accomplishments
and sense of satisfaction.
中文字幕
And that's normal, and rest assured that the scales will eventually tip more
toward happiness and away from sadness, but we'll
中文字幕
give you indeed more tools today than these for actually finding
problems or shortcomings in your code.
中文字幕
help50, recall, helps you with what process?
When you instinctively consider using help50?
中文字幕
When you see error messages on the screen.
Something you don't understand that's the result of some mistake you
中文字幕
probably made but you don't quite understand what the computer is telling
you, run help50, and then that same command and we, the staff,
中文字幕
with our code will try to understand the message for you
and provide you with feedback.
中文字幕
style50 does exactly that.
It helps you see with red and green color coding exactly what spaces should
中文字幕
be there, shouldn't be there-- it just helps you pretty
your code so that you can read it better and other humans can as well.
中文字幕
And then printf, which is kind of like the coarsest tool in your tool box,
this is just helping you see not only messages you want to see,
中文字幕
but just the values of variables.
You can print ints and strings, whatever you want,
中文字幕
and then you can delete those lines of printf
once you're confident your program's working.
中文字幕
But that gets a little tedious, and honestly, as our programs get bigger,
we're going to want more powerful tools than like manually printing things
中文字幕
out, recompiling, rerunning, it very quickly it gets tedious.
And the goal of programming is not to be tedious, but to be empowering,
中文字幕
and that's where we'll step to today via this.
So CS50 IDE is sort of fancier version of what
中文字幕
you've been using called CS50 Sandbox, and in turn, CS50 Lab.
Now recall that both of those tools, the Sandbox and the Lab,
中文字幕
have a terminal window where you can type commands,
they have a code editor where you can actually write your code,
中文字幕
and then they have a file browser with icons and such
where you can actually see your files and folders.
中文字幕
So it turns out that CS50 IDE is another tool that at first glance
is very, very similar, even though it's laid out a little differently,
中文字幕
but it has as many features as the Sandbox and the Lab, but some more.
More features that actually help you solve problems in your code
中文字幕
and even collaborate come final project time with others if you would like.
So this we'll see is this is the CS50 IDE.
中文字幕
It comes with the so-called night mode so you
can make everything a little darker on your screen, especially if p-setting
中文字幕
at night, and let's actually take a look then
at what you can do with this kind of tool.
中文字幕
When you log into this tool for the very first time in the next problem set,
you'll see an interface that's almost the same as before.
中文字幕
The colors are a little different, the font sizes are a little different,
but at the bottom by default, you have your so-called terminal window,
中文字幕
though instead of the dollar sign now, you'll
see a little more detailed workspace, but more on that in a bit.
中文字幕
Up here you just have the code editor window,
nothing's really going on there.
中文字幕
And then we have the added feature of Ceiling Cat
in the top right-hand corner.
中文字幕
And we'll also see some other features along the way.
So let's actually write a program in CS50 IDE, which, to be clear,
中文字幕
is just another web-based programming environment that also gives you
access to your own cloud-based server.
中文字幕
It, too, is running Ubuntu Linux, which is a popular operating system that
is not macOS and it's not Windows.
中文字幕
But unlike the sandbox environment where you don't even log in
and you lose your files eventually, as you
中文字幕
may know from when your cookies are lost or something goes wrong,
the IDE saves everything.
中文字幕
And you'll log in with your account, and whatever
you put there last week is going to be there this week and next week
中文字幕
and beyond.
So let me go ahead up to File, New File, or I could just click this little plus
中文字幕
icon in the top right-hand corner, and let me go ahead and preemptively hit
Control-S or Command-S or go to File, Save--
中文字幕
you should find the interface very similar to any Mac or PC program--
and let me go ahead and save this file as follows.
中文字幕
I'm going to call this hello.c.
And it's important to mention the file extension,
中文字幕
otherwise the IDE, like the Sandbox and the Lab,
won't know what type of program you're writing.
中文字幕
And then let me go ahead and just write my simplest of programs.
So let me go ahead and include stdio.h, int main void.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and open my curly braces, printf--
hello, world, backslash n, and a semi-colon.
中文字幕
So you'll notice that almost everything is the same.
The colors are a little different, perhaps,
中文字幕
and you might see some different assistive
features as you're typing your code, but the end result is the same.
中文字幕
And the color coding you just get for free because it's helping
draw your attention to different parts of the code.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead now and--
oh notice this.
中文字幕
There's one difference.
The IDE is a more powerful tool, but as such, it's a more manual tool
中文字幕
and it's not just going to auto-save your code for you.
Nice as that's been with the Sandbox, such that you'd never
中文字幕
actually had the hit Command-S or Control-S--
and if you were, you didn't need to be, the IDE
中文字幕
is only going to save things when you want it to so that nothing
will happen magically anymore.
中文字幕
So what I'm going to have to do is go back up here, File, Save, or Command-S
or Control-S, you'll see a little green dot
中文字幕
briefly, and now and back at my prompt.
I'm going to go ahead now and type my familiar command, make hello, Enter,
中文字幕
and you'll see pretty much the same cryptic-looking client
command as before because the IDE is configured quite like the Sandbox.
中文字幕
And if I want to go ahead and run this now, how do I run this program?
Quick check?
中文字幕
./hello, it's exactly the same as before.
./hello, and there we have it, hello, world.
中文字幕
So long story short, the user interface thus far is a little different,
but functionally it's the same.
中文字幕
We're just going to now start to see some more features.
So what are those features?
中文字幕
And let's introduce new some capabilities that were actually
possible in the Sandbox, we just didn't really introduce them at the time.
中文字幕
If I click this folder icon at top left, you'll see all of my files and folders.
And today for lecture I have a lot of pre-made examples
中文字幕
that are already on the course's website, some of which we'll look at,
some of which we'll refer to the website,
中文字幕
but these are just familiar files and folders.
And you can see that everything in my account
中文字幕
is apparently in something called Workspace, which
is just a folder, name, or a directory.
中文字幕
Here's my sc3 directory, which again, comes
from the website for today's lecture, lecture 3.
中文字幕
And then here's the file I just compiled in the program and the file
that I wrote, hello.c.
中文字幕
You'll notice too that there's this funky symbol here, tilde,
that you might not have occasion to write often in English,
中文字幕
but in Spanish in other languages you might use this character.
This is actually a shorthand notation for what's called your home directory.
中文字幕
In this environment, CS50 IDE, you have your own home directory, which
means your folder of files and other folders that you get to create,
中文字幕
you own, and that persists every time you log in-- you're not
going to lose the contents therein.
中文字幕
So this just means that in your home directory, a.k.a. tilde,
there is a folder called workspace in which I'm currently working.
中文字幕
And that's just one folder in which all of my work is going to be done,
because there's so many other files and folders in this cloud environment,
中文字幕
just like there are in your Mac and PC, we just generally
don't care what they are.
中文字幕
But notice what we can do at this terminal window besides compile
and run code.
中文字幕
There are other commands.
For instance, this blue text here, similarly to the file browser up top,
中文字幕
indicates now not just that this is my prompt per the dollar sign,
but that in my home directory's workspace directory.
中文字幕
So that means I can be elsewhere even though I haven't
specified where I want to go yet.
中文字幕
And in fact, I can do this. ls stands for list,
it's just shorthand notation for that.
中文字幕
And now I see a textual version of my file tree, so to speak.
So you'll see here, sc3 is a folder, and you
中文字幕
can tell as much because there's a slash at the end of it.
hello.c is of course the file I wrote a moment ago.
中文字幕
And then hello in green is my program that I compiled, and the star
or asterisk there is just--
中文字幕
it's not the name of the file, it's just indicating to me
visually that that is executable.
中文字幕
That's a program I can run just so I know what's compiled
and what maybe is source code.
中文字幕
So when you're running ./hello, the reason all this time this has been
working is because in dot, your current folder, there is a file called hello,
中文字幕
and when you hit Enter, you are running that program there.
So if after today you go back onto CS50 Sandbox or CS50 Lab and type ls,
中文字幕
you'll see exactly the same thing as you might by the little folder
icon in those programs as well.
中文字幕
But suppose I want to go into a directory.
In macOS or Windows or even the IDE, I could, of course,
中文字幕
go my File icon, and then per the little triangle
here, which might seem intuitive, you just click it
中文字幕
and you can see what's going on inside, not surprising.
But how do you do that textually?
中文字幕
At a command prompt, well it's not all that hard.
You just need to change your directory.
中文字幕
So if I do cd space sc3, Enter, nothing seems to happen quite yet
except that my prompt changed.
中文字幕
Here's the indication that-- this is my prompt, but to the left of it
you see in blue that I'm now in my home directory's workspace folder,
中文字幕
in my sc3 folder there.
So it's just a text-based version of the GUIs, the Graphical User Interfaces
中文字幕
that all of us have certainly come to take
for granted in the world of macOS and Windows thus far.
中文字幕
Well, suppose that I'm a little done with my hello program
and I want to delete it.
中文字幕
Well in the IDE, like in the Sandbox, you can actually go up here and you can
click on it, and then you can typically right-click or control-click,
中文字幕
and you'll get a whole menu of other options, one of which is Delete--
and feel free to tinker like that in your own environment.
中文字幕
But what about the command line?
If I zoom in down here and I want to remove hello, you're
中文字幕
not going to type remove because that just feels a little verbose
and humans decades ago decided that's too tedious to type,
中文字幕
let's just call this command rm--
for remove-- hello, you're going to see a somewhat cryptic prompt.
中文字幕
rm-- remove regular file 'hello?'
This is more arcane than it needs to be, but it's just asking,
中文字幕
are you sure you want to delete 'hello?'
Then it's just waiting for you.
中文字幕
And here you can type y or yes or sometimes other commands too,
now I've confirmed that my intentions were yes.
中文字幕
If I type ls again, I-- whoops, in the wrong folder.
If I type ls again after doing hello--
中文字幕
no-- after doing hello and do ls, now I'll
see just those two things-- sc3 and hello.c.
中文字幕
What if I want to make a folder?
Well notice this.
中文字幕
If I type at the bottom here, make directory--
mkdir-- test just to make a test folder, I'm
中文字幕
about to hit Enter, but watch the top left-hand corner
where I currently have those other files and folders, and when I hit Enter,
中文字幕
now I have a test folder.
So these things are identical.
中文字幕
One is graphical, one is command line, and there's even other commands
if I decide I don't want that.
中文字幕
rmdir is remove directory, and it just goes away
because it's empty and thus safe.
中文字幕
Any questions then on any of those commands
or just the overall layout of what it is we're looking at?
中文字幕
All right, so don't get hung up on any of those commands,
and the problem set and beyond will always
中文字幕
remind you of those kinds of features.
The point for now is just that we're in a somewhat new environment,
中文字幕
but it's fundamentally still the same, it has the same capabilities.
So what are other tools we looked at?
中文字幕
So you might have heard rumors about a tool called check50, and indeed,
this is a tool that the staff use to evaluate problem set 1 and problems set
中文字幕
2 to evaluate the correctness of them so that we ourselves don't have to type
./mario or ./caesar again and again and again to test students' code.
中文字幕
But starting this week, you, too, have access to the same program.
check50 is a command from the staff that checks the correctness of your code
中文字幕
just like style50 checks the style of your code.
And in fact, if I go back over to my IDE,
中文字幕
let's try to use this for the first time by making the same version of hello
that you did perhaps for your first problem set.
中文字幕
So if I go ahead and include not just stdio, but cs50.h,
and I go ahead and get a string from the user
中文字幕
with get_string, prompting them for their name, and then go ahead
and print not just hello, world, but hello, percent s comma name,
中文字幕
this I believe was the same program you yourselves probably
wrote, or some variant thereof.
中文字幕
So if I go ahead now and test this myself--
make hello, Enter, seems OK, ./hello.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead and type in my name, and voila, hello, David.
Now suppose you're feeling pretty good, you're
中文字幕
pretty confident that your code is correct,
and most importantly, you have tested your code yourselves.
中文字幕
It's not sufficient to rely on our tool alone
to test your code because it, too, might not be exhaustive.
中文字幕
So once you've tried a few inputs, not just David, but perhaps
Veronica's name as well, seems to work.
中文字幕
Brian's name as well, seems to work.
No name at all, doesn't seem to work, maybe?
中文字幕
But we'll have to look back to the problem set
to see if that's actually a problem.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead now and run check50.
check50 expects a special slug, so to speak.
中文字幕
Just a unique identifier for the problem that you want to check.
And you would only know this from reading a problem
中文字幕
set or a documentation online.
I just happened to recall that the command that the staff had been using
中文字幕
to grade and evaluate hello is just cs50/2018/fall/hello.
And the slash is to just kind of visually distinguish those words,
中文字幕
this isn't a folder or files or anything like that in your own account.
So I'm going to run check50 cs50/2018/fall/hello in the same
中文字幕
directory that hello.c is in.
Enter.
中文字幕
It's going to go ahead and connect to GitHub, which is the backend,
recall, that we use for storing your code.
中文字幕
It's authenticating me now, which means what's your username and password?
I'm going to go ahead and use one of my test accounts.
中文字幕
And now it's prompting me for my password,
and I'm going to go ahead and type that in.
中文字幕
You'll notice you're seeing stars like you see bullets in a website
just so that someone looking over your shoulder can't see what you're typing.
中文字幕
Now I'm going to go ahead and watch the progress.
It's preparing, let me go ahead and zoom in.
中文字幕
Dot-dot-dot.
It's looking at my code, it's getting ready for submission,
中文字幕
it's now uploading it to GitHub.com, and once it's on the servers,
then it's going to tell CS50 server, here is so-and-so's submission,
中文字幕
go ahead and run a few automated tests on it,
checking therefore its correctness, and hopefully we're about to see some
中文字幕
green, happy smiley faces, and voila, yes,
it looks like this check50 command for this problem--
中文字幕
or slug, so to speak--
checked that hello.c exists, because if I forgot to write the file
中文字幕
or if I misnamed it, nothing's going to work.
We checked that it compiles successfully,
中文字幕
so that, too, is a happy green face.
Then it apparently checked--
中文字幕
what if we type in Veronica?
Do we see hello, Veronica?
中文字幕
Apparently yes.
What if we typed in another word, Brian?
中文字幕
Yes, apparently we say hello, Brian.
And so with high probability, we're going
中文字幕
to conclude, based on those four tests, that your code is, in fact, correct,
at least with respect to those inputs.
中文字幕
And there's often some more detail via URL at the bottom
where you can actually see more graphically just more
中文字幕
feedback on your code.
Of course, the first time, second time, third time maybe you run this command,
中文字幕
you might not see some green happy faces,
you might see some red unhappy faces or some yellow flat faces,
中文字幕
which just means we couldn't even run the checks because something else is
wrong.
中文字幕
But over time, this will help you feel more comfortable and more confident
that your code's correct before you actually use submit50 and submit.
中文字幕
Going into it you'll feel a little better or a little frustrated
to know in advance-- wait a minute, I'm about to submit this but nope,
中文字幕
it's not yet correct.
So realize it's a two-edged sword.
中文字幕
Any questions about check50 or any of these commands thus far?
Anything at all?
中文字幕
No?
All right.
中文字幕
So let's take a look at the final and most powerful
tool now available to you in the IDE environment.
中文字幕
Built in to CS50 IDE, which stands for Integrated Development
Environment, which isn't a CS50 thing-- this is a common term in industry
中文字幕
for tools that make it easier to write code,
it turns out that there's some other feature besides the cat over here.
中文字幕
Namely, one, you can share your workspace
with teaching fellows and course assistants
中文字幕
so they can perhaps help you in real time a la Google Docs, even chatting
with you in real time.
中文字幕
But it also provides you with what's called a debugger.
A debugger, as the name suggests, removes bugs--
中文字幕
or rather, helps you remove bugs from your code
by allowing you to not just resort to printf--
中文字幕
printing out ints and strings and whatever
is good that's going on your program, it kind of automates
中文字幕
that very tedious process for you.
And it lets you walk through your code one
中文字幕
line at a time at your own comfortable pace
and see along the way all of the values of your variables in that program.
中文字幕
To activate this debugger, I'm going to go ahead and do the following.
I'm going to compile my code as always with make hello.
中文字幕
It has to compile, otherwise I might want
to use help50 and figure out why it's not compiling,
中文字幕
but it does seem to have compiled.
And now I'm going to go ahead and run debug50, space, and then
中文字幕
the name of the program I wanted to debug.
And the name of the program I wanted to debug at the moment
中文字幕
is the current directory's file called hello.
Let's assume that there's perhaps something wrong with it.
中文字幕
The first time I run this command, though, debug50
is not going to be happy with me because it's going to say,
中文字幕
it looks like you haven't set any breakpoints.
Set at least one breakpoint by clicking to the left of a line number
中文字幕
and then rerun debug50.
Well what is a breakpoint?
中文字幕
Well as the name kind of suggests, it allows
you to break or pause the running of your code at any of your lines.
中文字幕
And all this time for the past few weeks,
your code been automatically line-numbered.
中文字幕
And this is useful because the most interesting line in this program,
once it really gets going, isn't this stuff at the top,
中文字幕
it's not int main void, right?
That's all copy-paste from past programs.
中文字幕
It's really the sixth line here where I actually have some logic of my own.
And so in CS50 IDE, what you can now do is
中文字幕
click to the left of one of these line numbers,
a little red light like a stop sign is going to appear saying,
中文字幕
break or pause my program on this line so
that I can poke around my actual code.
中文字幕
Sandbox and Lab cannot do this.
So now I'm going to go ahead and rerun debug50 in exactly the same way, hit
中文字幕
Enter, but now I have one breakpoint.
And you'll see on the right-hand side a fancier menu just popped up
中文字幕
by the cat that provides me with a bunch of features.
And at first glance, frankly, it's a little overwhelming
中文字幕
because there's a lot going on here, but you'll notice first,
and most importantly, there's some mention of my name variable.
中文字幕
I don't quite understand 0x0 or whatnot, but I do understand string.
And so what the debug50 program has realized is oh, on this line and below,
中文字幕
you have a variable called name.
It doesn't seem to have a value yet.
中文字幕
0x0, it turns out, is just going to mean empty or null or 0.
But that's good, because now, when I actually execute this line,
中文字幕
hopefully it's going to take on the name David or Veronica or Brian.
So let's see what happens.
中文字幕
Notice that it's highlighted in yellow, line 6, which means it
has not yet executed this line of code.
中文字幕
My code has paused at this point because I set that breakpoint.
And then notice kind of like a music player up here, there's a few icons.
中文字幕
The Play button is just going to say, ah, play my program,
run it all the way through the end, kind of like scratch with the green flag.
中文字幕
But more powerful is this.
You can step over this line, therefore executing it just once.
中文字幕
If it's a function, you can step into this line
and actually look inside of a function that you're using, like get_string,
中文字幕
or you can step out of another function, but more on that another time.
So what I'm going to do is this.
中文字幕
And the button I'm going to click most commonly when trying to understand
how my program is working is this--
中文字幕
Step Over.
So it's the second icon from the left, right next to the triangle.
中文字幕
So once I click this, watch what's going to happen,
even though it's a little small, on the right-hand side for my name variable.
中文字幕
Notice that I'm being prompted to type in my name because the program
is still running in my terminal window, but when I hit Enter now,
中文字幕
providing my own name, automatically you see on the right-hand side
that this name variable has a value now of, quote-unquote,
中文字幕
"David" of type string.
There's this 0x1083010-- more on that later, just a little cryptic,
中文字幕
but I didn't have to use printf now, I can actually see what's going on.
Now you can see that line 7 is highlighted,
中文字幕
because I set a breakpoint above it, so now I'm on the second line
because I just stepped into it.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and click Next again, and you'll
see that in my terminal window, hello, David just got executed.
中文字幕
And now if I just keep going, it's going to go ahead and run to the end
and close the debugger.
中文字幕
So not all that useful for this program because frankly, I'm
pretty sure this is correct, but the power of debug50 and a debugger more
中文字幕
generally is that it lets you, whether you're less comfy or more comfy,
walk through your own code at your pace just like a TF or a CA might say, OK,
中文字幕
what is this line doing?
What is this line doing?
中文字幕
You don't have to resort to printf, you can just very methodically
walk through your code and find that damn bug that's been bothering you
中文字幕
for minutes or even hours.
So henceforth, any time you have a bug in your code that is compiling
中文字幕
but it's just logically incorrect-- the pyramid in Mario isn't quite right,
your encryption of Caesar isn't quite right, or something else,
中文字幕
your first instinct now should be, let me compile it, run debug50 on it,
and just step through the code, setting a breakpoint wherever I want,
中文字幕
so you focus on just a few lines, not the whole thing--
like I just did--
中文字幕
and see if you can figure out logically when a value is not what you expected,
then oh--
中文字幕
go ahead and just click Resume, fix the bug, and retry.
Such a powerful tool.
中文字幕
Any questions?
Yeah?
中文字幕
What is it?
AUDIENCE: What does it look like when there is a bug?
中文字幕
What does it look like when there is a bug?
So the debugger won't find your bugs and it won't show you your bugs, per se.
中文字幕
It's going to let you see what line is executing,
it's going to let you see what's outputting,
中文字幕
it's going to let you take input, but all it's
going to do on that right-hand side is just show
中文字幕
you the values of things along the way.
It's up to you to infer from that information what
中文字幕
it is that's going wrong, just like if you're using printf in past weeks
to see what's going on in your program.
中文字幕
Other questions?
And let me save this too.
中文字幕
It is so easy to get into the habit, especially when so many things have
been new over the past few weeks of just saying, ah,
中文字幕
this is just yet another thing to learn.
This is hands down the kind of tool that if you
中文字幕
spend a few extra minutes this week and next week just using it,
get a little more comfortable with it, it
中文字幕
will save you potentially hours in the long run,
because all the time you've been spending manually
中文字幕
trying to fix your bugs or posting questions online
trying to understand things, this is a tool
中文字幕
that if you invest those minutes upfront will just
help you understand everything going on inside of your program,
中文字幕
and will absolutely over the next few weeks save you more and more time.
All right, any questions? yeah?
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: So you have a for loop that ran [INAUDIBLE] times,
[INAUDIBLE] separate break statements so you don't have to [INAUDIBLE]..
中文字幕
Ah, good question.
If you have something like a for loop or a while loop, something
中文字幕
that's happening a lot, can you set a breakpoint in such a way
that it only breaks so that you don't have to walk through it 100 times
中文字幕
just to see that value?
Short answer, yes.
中文字幕
And let me defer to section and online resources for just a few
of these features, but one, you can actually watch values,
中文字幕
and you can have what's called a watch expression.
You can say show me this value if only when x is greater than 50
中文字幕
or something like that.
Or you yourself can just add some lines of code.
中文字幕
You could add a, if x equals-equals 50, then print out something,
and you can set a breakpoint on that new, if temporary line,
中文字幕
so there's a couple of ways to do that.
Good question to anticipate.
中文字幕
Yeah?
Behind.
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: If you run debug50, aren't you adding
another arugment with the [INAUDIBLE] in your main method at line 4?
中文字幕
Really good question.
If you're running debug50, aren't you adding
中文字幕
another argument-- argv-- per our discussion last week of command line
arguments?
中文字幕
Short answer, no, because debug50 corrects for that,
so you don't have to worry about that.
中文字幕
It will not shift things over numerically.
Really good thought.
中文字幕
Other questions?
All right, so with that said, let's now take some training wheels off.
中文字幕
So the only reason I bought these training wheels years ago
is to make this very dramatic point of now taking the training wheels off
中文字幕
today.
OK, so what does this mean?
中文字幕
Well worth the trip to Target.
So what does this mean?
中文字幕
For the past few weeks, we have been using a whole bunch
of functions from CS50's library.
中文字幕
All of these were meant to just make it pretty easy, relatively speaking,
in the first few weeks to get input from the user.
中文字幕
Because it turns out, as we'll see today,
it's actually a kind of a pain in the neck to get input from users in C,
中文字幕
and frankly, even in other languages reliability.
Because you'll recall that get_string and get_int and all of these functions
中文字幕
take on the burden of like re-prompting the user if they don't actually
give you an an int or don't give you a float
中文字幕
or don't give you a char that you're expecting, they'll re-prompt,
they're using a while loop or a do-while loop or the like,
中文字幕
so there's just a lot of error detection built into these functions.
But, most importantly-- and most misleadingly,
中文字幕
has been the last one on this list.
Recall that we introduced a couple weeks ago now the notion of a string.
中文字幕
And a string is in English what?
An array of characters, good.
中文字幕
It's a sequence of characters, and we learned last week that a sequence can
be implemented in an array, which is just a chunk of memory
中文字幕
back-to-back-to-back-to-back.
So string, though, is not quite like any of those other data types.
中文字幕
It turns out that it's not quite like int or char or even bool or float,
and we can start to see that now as follows.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead and go into the IDE today--
and henceforth we're going to just start using the IDE,
中文字幕
but you're welcome to keep using the Sandbox for quick and dirty programs,
but for anything you want to keep around,
中文字幕
your instinct should now be to open your IDE.
I'm going to go ahead and create a new file,
中文字幕
and I'm going to call it compare0.c from my first example of comparing things.
And I'm going to go ahead and whip up a relatively short program
中文字幕
that you would hope would work right out of the box.
So I'm going to go ahead and include the familiar cs50.h.
中文字幕
I'm going to go include stdio.h.
I'm going to go ahead and do int main void.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead and in here--
let me a variable called i using get_int from the user,
中文字幕
and just prompt them for i.
Let me go ahead then and prompt the user for another get_int.
中文字幕
We'll call it j and get that from them.
And then let's just compare these things.
中文字幕
So if i equals-equals j, then go ahead and print out
with printf same and a new line.
中文字幕
Then go ahead and print out the opposite, which is different.
So the only place I think I could have screwed up, perhaps,
中文字幕
is if I did this, which is kind of reasonable if you
come in knowing what an equal sign is.
中文字幕
But again, in code, we typically need two equal signs
because that compares two values.
中文字幕
So I didn't make that mistake, I'm feeling pretty good about this.
Let me save it with Command-S or Control-S or via File,
中文字幕
Save; go to my prompt and run make compare0.
Good, everything compiled.
中文字幕
And let me go ahead and run compare0, Enter, and I'll type in 50,
and I'll type in 50, and they do seem to be the same.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and do that again, let's type in 42 and 13,
and they are different.
中文字幕
And I should probably test a few more, maybe some negative values, maybe some
0's, positive values and the like, but I'm
中文字幕
feeling pretty good about the correctness of this code.
All right.
中文字幕
So let's change this program a bit.
Let me go ahead and create another file, which
中文字幕
I can do with the little green plus or via File, New File.
I'm going to go ahead save this one as compare1.c.
中文字幕
And for the moment I'm going to go ahead and just paste in that code
from before, but I'm going to make some changes now.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead and rename and retype my data types as strings.
So give me a string called s, and will prompt the user
中文字幕
for that using get_string, then I'm going
to go ahead and change this 1 to string t,
中文字幕
and I'm going to go ahead and get get_string.
I, of course, need to now compare s and t, not i and j.
中文字幕
And s is a common variable name for a string. t just comes after s,
so that's pretty reasonable too, but I should of course update that as well.
中文字幕
And so I think everything's now the same logically.
I just changed my data types and my variable names.
中文字幕
So I've saved this.
Let me go ahead and run make compare1.
中文字幕
Good, everything's correct.
Let me go ahead and do ./compare1.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and type in Brian and Veronica.
And of course, those are different.
中文字幕
Now let me go ahead and type in David, let me type in David again,
and those of course are different?
中文字幕
Huh.
Maybe it's because I just hit the Spacebar or something.
中文字幕
So let's try Erin.
Her name's a little shorter.
中文字幕
Hmm.
OK, let's try-- oh, what's her name?
中文字幕
TJ.
OK, even shorter, perfect.
中文字幕
TJ, can't go wrong.
Different.
中文字幕
I mean, what is going on?
Let's just say i, i.
中文字幕
Different?
So where's the logical bug in this program?
中文字幕
What is it that's going on?
Yeah, what do you think?
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: Is it comparing integer values?
Is it comparing integer values?
中文字幕
Well maybe.
I mean, thus far when we've used equal-equals
中文字幕
we've probably used it mostly for comparing integers,
so maybe I'm just misusing it, sure.
中文字幕
Other thoughts?
Oh, that's a big word that we'll get to in just a little bit.
中文字幕
But correct, correct-- but for very similar reasons.
So something's going on logically involving comparison,
中文字幕
because I'm using equal-equal, but maybe I'm using it for the wrong data types?
I mean, it's clearly broken for strings.
中文字幕
So why might that actually be?
Well it turns out that strings don't actually exist.
中文字幕
So a string that we know is just a sequence of characters
or an array of characters is not an actual data type.
中文字幕
int is, float is, double is, long is, bool is, and even more
are actual data types.
中文字幕
String is kind of a little white lie we've
been telling for a few weeks that's implemented only in the CS50 library.
中文字幕
Now the word string is super common in programming.
Like every programmer out there will know what you mean when you say string.
中文字幕
That is not a CS50 word, but our use of it in C is CS50-specific.
Because in that file called cs50.h, in addition
中文字幕
to declaring functions like get_string and get_int and get_float
and a bunch of other things, we also have a special line that says,
中文字幕
create a data type called string.
But what does it actually do or what does it actually mean?
中文字幕
Well let's go ahead and consider what might be going on underneath the hood
here.
中文字幕
So if I go ahead and draw the program that we just
ran, that program compare1 gets a string s from the user,
中文字幕
then gets a string t from the user, and then compares them.
So we know from last week what a string is, it's just an array.
中文字幕
So when I run that first line of code and get a string from the user--
for instance, Brian, I'm going to go ahead and see a B-R-I-A-N,
中文字幕
which we know from last week to actually be an array of memory that might look
pictorially like this-- and this, too, is a bit of a white lie,
中文字幕
there's something else.
AUDIENCE: The null.
中文字幕
Yeah, the null character, so to speak, and ul,
which we typically just write with a backslash 0, which is just all 0 bits.
中文字幕
And it turns out, you might recall from the debugger earlier, you saw this--
that's the even more cryptic way of expressing the null character,
中文字幕
backslash 0.
Just different programs display it in different ways.
中文字幕
So when I get_string and type in Brian, this is what's allocated in memory.
And when I type Veronica, I can see a V-E-R-O-N-I-C-A.
中文字幕
I'm going to get that right preemptively.
Backslash 0.
中文字幕
That, too, is a chunk of memory, which I'll draw like this.
1, 2, and split these up into interval characters or bytes.
中文字幕
And recall from last time that these bytes just come from my memory,
and that memory just has a bunch of bytes in it, maybe millions or even
中文字幕
billions these days.
And so honestly, if you just have that many things,
中文字幕
any human or computer can certainly number them.
Like this is byte 1, 2, 3, 4.
中文字幕
So let's just assume for the sake of discussion
that out of context of my computer's hardware,
中文字幕
Brian just ended up at location 100, and location 101, and 102, 103, 104, 105.
So this is the 100th byte in my computer,
中文字幕
this is 105th byte in my computer, and Brian
is using that many characters in total.
中文字幕
Veronica, she ended up somewhere else.
Maybe she ended up farther away just because at location 900, 901, 902, 903,
中文字幕
904, 905, 906-- a lot more memory, 907, and 908--
but you can see even more visually now that the length of Brian's name--
中文字幕
strlen of Brian is what?
I hear five and I hear six.
中文字幕
The length of Brian's name--
Brian, how long is your name?
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: Five.
OK, it is definitively five characters, that
中文字幕
is the length of Brian's name, but you have
to appreciate that in the computer, Brian's five-character name does indeed
中文字幕
take up six bytes.
So both answers are kind of correct, but the length of the string henceforth
中文字幕
is always the number of actual characters.
The amount of space it takes up is that plus 1 for the null character.
中文字幕
So you can actually see why Brian's name takes up six bytes in this picture
rather than just the actual length, which is five.
中文字幕
So when you call get_string now, and when you call
get_string and get another string--
中文字幕
Brian and Veronica respectively, what is actually being handed back?
A couple weeks ago, Erin came up and she kind of like
中文字幕
handed me back a string, a student's name from the audience.
On that piece of paper we thought was the student's name.
中文字幕
But it's not.
It turns out that when a function returns a value,
中文字幕
it can pretty much only return a 1 byte or maybe 2 or 4 bytes.
It can't return an arbitrary number of bytes, like six for Brian or 1, 2, 3,
中文字幕
4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9-- it cannot return 9 bytes for Veronica.
And if you even type a whole paragraph or page of text,
中文字幕
it can't return all of that text, it can only return a single value.
So to your instinct earlier, what might actually
中文字幕
be getting returned by get_string when the human has
typed in a name like Brian or Veronica?
中文字幕
The memory location.
Indeed, an integer, or as you called it, a pointer,
中文字幕
which we'll introduce more formally in just a moment.
So when get_string string returns "Brian," quote-unquote,
中文字幕
it's actually not returning B-R-I-A-N backslash 0, it is just returning 100.
And when get_string returns Veronica, it's not returning her name,
中文字幕
it's returning 900.
And so if you realize that now, when you do does
中文字幕
s equal-equal t, what question more mundanely are you actually asking?
Yeah.
中文字幕
Memory location and memory location-- does 100 equal 900?
And obviously not.
中文字幕
And so that is why Brian's name, Veronica's name,
my name, TJ's name-- every word I typed in was of course different,
中文字幕
because each input was ending up at a different location in memory.
And even if I typed the same word like David twice, one David was going here,
中文字幕
one David was going somewhere else, they were ending up
at different memory locations.
中文字幕
Maybe 100, maybe 900, maybe something else,
but they were ending up in different locations in memory.
中文字幕
So equal-equals does compare values, but dammit
if it isn't comparing the wrong values.
中文字幕
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Well what if you use some char*s?
中文字幕
Ah, so we'll come back to that.
Let me come back to that in just a moment.
中文字幕
char* is actually intricately related.
More on that in a moment.
中文字幕
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: If you add two integers in memory--
中文字幕
Uh huh?
AUDIENCE: Wouldn't they be in different places in memory?
中文字幕
So you would return--
so you need a different value.
中文字幕
OK, really good question.
So wait a minute, this same logic that I'm returning the address of something
中文字幕
surely applies to integers as well or floating point values as well?
Because if I type in the number 50 like I
中文字幕
did earlier, that, too, is somewhere in memory-- like a box in memory,
and that, too, has an address somewhere in memory,
中文字幕
but it turns out, for reasons that you just alluded to, actually,
ints are returned as their values.
中文字幕
Chars are returned as their values.
Bools are returned as their values.
中文字幕
Floats are returned as their values.
Strings are different.
中文字幕
Strings are returned by their address.
And those addresses, it turns out, are ultimately going to be called
中文字幕
char*'s, which we'll see in just a moment.
So how do we go about then fixing this fundamentally?
中文字幕
Like even if you have no idea how to code this yet, just intuitively,
if I do actually want to delete--
中文字幕
if I do actually want to compare--
sorry.
中文字幕
OK.
If I do want to go ahead and compare Brian and Veronica for equality,
中文字幕
what do I want to do intuitively?
I can't just compare their addresses.
中文字幕
What do I need to do?
Isolate the characters and then do what with them?
中文字幕
Good.
Yeah, good instincts.
中文字幕
Use a for loop, use a while loop-- any kind of looping structure.
And intuitively, compare the first characters,
中文字幕
and if they're different, well then we know we don't have to go any further.
B is not a V, so surely these names are different.
中文字幕
But what about in my case?
If it was David and David, you would compare the first two.
中文字幕
D and D are the same.
Compare the second two, A and A are the same.
中文字幕
V and V, I and I, D and D, and then what am I going to hit last?
Null character.
中文字幕
And should I keep going beyond the null character?
No.
中文字幕
So this is the beauty of that super simple design for a string.
Insofar as strings are identified by their starting address, just the byte
中文字幕
at which they start, you still need to know
how long they are, because otherwise how do where one word begins and ends
中文字幕
and another word begins?
And so the simple decision we made last week-- as did humans decades ago--
中文字幕
to terminate all strings with backslash 0 or all 0's is a super handy trick,
so that if I tell you that Brian starts at 100,
中文字幕
you can infer that he ends where?
At byte number 105 or 104, if you will, however you want to think about it,
中文字幕
because all you need to do in linear time,
if you will, left or right, is check-- backslash 0, backslash 0-- ah!
中文字幕
Backslash 0, now I know how long Brian's name is.
So let's consider for a moment this program called string length.
中文字幕
How does strlen actually work?
When you pass to strlen, a variable containing a string, like Brian,
中文字幕
what is sterling probably doing?
Exactly.
中文字幕
It's looking at that null character's address
and subtracting the start address and the end address,
中文字幕
figuring out what the difference is, and actually returning
that minus 1 the total count.
中文字幕
And more mechanically, we'll see in a moment,
it's probably doing exactly the same thing I did,
中文字幕
which is, is this backslash 0?
Is this backslash 0?
中文字幕
Is this, is this, is this?
I asked that question five times before I saw backslash 0.
中文字幕
strlen is just a function some human wrote years ago
that probably just has a simple for loop and an if condition,
中文字幕
and then that's it.
Because that person understood before we even
中文字幕
did how strings are actually implemented.
Any questions then?
中文字幕
All right, so let's actually implement this.
Let me go ahead and into my editor here, and make one other example here
中文字幕
that I'm going to call compare2.
I'm going to go ahead and do include cs50.h and include stdio.h,
中文字幕
and then I'm going to do int main void, and I'm
going to quickly now grab my code from before where I got strings
中文字幕
and I compared them, but I have to obviously fix that comparison.
So here's my code from before.
中文字幕
I'm going to do this the right way.
I'm going to call a function called compare_strings passing in s and t.
中文字幕
Because as you proposed, we need to do some logic.
We don't have to pass it to a function, but we could.
中文字幕
We could just do a for loop here, but I'm
going to go ahead and implement compare_strings as follows.
中文字幕
If I want to write a function that returns a yes/no answer, what data type
should it return?
中文字幕
A bool.
So we've not necessarily done this yet, but you
中文字幕
can return a bool just like you can int or a char or something else.
I'm going to call this function compare_strings.
中文字幕
It's going to take in one string called a and another string called b,
but I could call those anything I want.
中文字幕
And now what's the easiest thing to check?
If I pass two strings, a and b, or Brian and Veronica,
中文字幕
what's the easiest question you can ask and just immediately say, nope,
these are different?
中文字幕
String length, right?
Like if the B-R-I-A-N is not of the same length as Veronica's name,
中文字幕
we don't need to do any logic whatsoever beyond that,
we can just quit and say false.
中文字幕
So let me just do that.
If the strlen of a does not equal the strlen of b, you know what?
中文字幕
Let's just go ahead and return false and get out of here.
OK, but now, if we get past that gateway, so to speak,
中文字幕
that check, that question, that Boolean expression,
now I have to compare things character by character by character.
中文字幕
So I can do this in a bunch of ways, but I like the suggestion of a for loop.
So for int i at 0, n for efficiency-- actually,
中文字幕
let's do i is less than the string length--
should I do the string length of a or b?
中文字幕
And it doesn't matter, right?
So let's go with a.
中文字幕
And frankly, had I been smart early on, I
could have stored the value in a variable and then reused it,
中文字幕
but we'll just keep going ahead for now.
Then i plus-plus, but I remember from last time-- this is correct,
中文字幕
but this is not good design.
Why?
中文字幕
Yeah, I keep calling strlen again and again, because remember, in a for loop,
this condition is checked again and again
中文字幕
and again-- you're just wasting your own time.
So let me go ahead and actually do this.
中文字幕
n or any variable equals the strlen of a, then just compare i against n,
because now i is getting incremented, but n is never changing.
中文字幕
So now let me go ahead and implement this for loop.
So if-- how about the i-th character of a does not equal the i-th character
中文字幕
of b, I can immediately conclude--
nope, these strings can't be the same, because some letter, like a B,
中文字幕
is not the same as another, like a V, or whatever letter we're actually
comparing.
中文字幕
And then I think that's it.
If I get through these gauntlets of questions--
中文字幕
are yours lengths different?
Are your characters different?
中文字幕
And I still haven't said false, what should I return by default?
Yeah.
中文字幕
Like if you make it through all of those questions and all is well,
then D-A-V-I-D must indeed equal D-A-V-I-D or whatever the user actually
中文字幕
typed in.
Now I'm not quite done yet.
中文字幕
When I've implemented a function or a helper function
like this, because it's helping me do my work,
中文字幕
what else do I have to add to the file?
Oh?
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: I've got a logical question.
Sure.
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: In a computer, couldn't you just type in David with a capital D
and then david with a lowercase d, you're going to run [INAUDIBLE],,
中文字幕
they're not going to sync because your first character's not
the same character.
中文字幕
Correct.
So this is a feature, not a bug at the moment.
中文字幕
My program at the moment is case-sensitive.
If I type in DAVID and all caps, that is a different string
中文字幕
I claim for now than david in all lowercase.
If you want to tolerate uppercase and lowercase,
中文字幕
you're going have to add more logic.
But for now that's a design decision that I intend.
中文字幕
All right.
What else do I need to add to the program?
中文字幕
Yeah, the prototype at top.
You can literally copy and paste-- this is the only time copy and paste is
中文字幕
probably a legitimate thing to do--
at the top, and then semi-colon-- don't re-implement it.
中文字幕
But I do need one other header file.
I'm using a function that's not in cs50.h or in stdio.h.
中文字幕
String length?
Where was string length?
中文字幕
Yeah, string.h.
So I just need this, include string.h, save.
中文字幕
Now this I think is correct.
We'll see if I eat the word in a moment.
中文字幕
But realize that if you're writing this code yourself,
like this is not a natural thing to be writing a program in office hours
中文字幕
or at home in your dorm and just getting it right the first time.
This is after like 20 years of doing this, so realize we happen to be--
中文字幕
and I also have a cheat sheet right here--
we happen to be doing this correctly often,
中文字幕
but realize that's not going to be the common case.
So with that reassurance in mind, let's see
中文字幕
if I have to now take all that back. make compare2.
OK-- phew.
中文字幕
20 years worked out.
So now I'm going to go ahead and ./compare2.
中文字幕
Let's type in Brian, let's type in Veronica.
Those are indeed still different hopefully.
中文字幕
Now let's try myself, David and David.
Phew!
中文字幕
Those are the same.
And to your point, David in capitalized and David in all lowercase,
中文字幕
different, but that's what I expect now.
Any questions on compare2?
中文字幕
Yeah?
OK.
中文字幕
string in the program and in general.
OK.
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: Would that still work [INAUDIBLE]
If you were to hard code the strings?
中文字幕
Short answer, yes, that would still work.
If you for whatever reason did not do this and using get_string,
中文字幕
but you did David, and here, for instance, David, that would work too.
And whatever your error is, if you can recreate it, just let us know.
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: It seems to be like a string that would be increased
for a set that was [INAUDIBLE] only?
中文字幕
And it was having issues in the little [INAUDIBLE]..
I'd have to see it to be sure, but happy to chat after.
中文字幕
All right, so let's see if we can't now clean this
up just a little bit as follows.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead here and reveal what it is that's actually going on.
So indeed, there is no such thing as a string.
中文字幕
And indeed, as you pointed out a moment ago,
it actually goes by a different name.
中文字幕
String is just a synonym for what's called a char*.
Now what does that even mean?
中文字幕
So char is the same as it's always been.
It's a single character.
中文字幕
Star in a program written in C could of course mean multiplication,
we have seen that.
中文字幕
This is another use of the star.
Whenever you see it after a data type like char,
中文字幕
this means that the data type in question is not just a char,
it's the address of a char.
中文字幕
So the star just means the address of whatever the data type is to the left,
and this is, as you pointed out earlier, what
中文字幕
we're going to start calling a pointer.
A pointer is, for all intents and purposes, an address.
中文字幕
It's just a buzzword to describe an address.
This data type here, char*, means I want a variable that doesn't store a char,
中文字幕
it stores the address of a char.
The number 100, the number 900.
中文字幕
But that address is just going to be called a pointer.
A pointer variable is a variable that stores the address of something.
中文字幕
A char or even other data types as well.
So with that in mind, let me actually quickly create compare3.c, paste this
中文字幕
in, and save it as compare3.c, and let me take off, if you will,
those training wheels.
中文字幕
It turns out that when you get a string with get_string,
it doesn't return a string, per se, because again,
中文字幕
that word doesn't exist in C, it actually returns a char*.
And when I call it again here and return another string, it, too,
中文字幕
returns a char*.
Now technically the star can have spaces around it.
中文字幕
Some people write it like this, but the sort of right way to do it
or the default way should just be to put the star next to the variable name
中文字幕
for clarity.
So I have to make a few other changes.
中文字幕
This should change too, because there is no more string as of today.
I'm going to change this to a char*; and then I also need to change it here,
中文字幕
char*; and then here, char*; and that is actually it.
And honestly, the only reason we didn't introduce this like two weeks ago
中文字幕
is because it just looks cryptic.
Like no one wants to program the first time they're ever touching a keyboard
中文字幕
and writing code and see char* and need to worry about what that means,
it's just a string conceptually.
中文字幕
But the only change I technically need to make to take those training wheels
off is just change all mentions of string as data types to char*.
中文字幕
And that just means that you know what-- a?
Yes it's a string, but more technically it's the address of a string.
中文字幕
Or more precisely, it is the address of the first byte of the string,
like 100 for Brian or 900 for Veronica, and I'm not even
中文字幕
going to tell you where the string ends because you, the programmer,
can figure that out by calling strlen or just by using a loop
中文字幕
and figuring out where that backslash 0 actually is.
So that is enough information to pass it around.
中文字幕
So if go ahead now and compile this, make compare3,
and then I go ahead and do ./compare3, let's go ahead and type in Brian
中文字幕
and Veronica, those are indeed still different.
Now let me go ahead and type in David and David, those are in fact the same.
中文字幕
So the training wheels are off, there is no such thing as string,
henceforth it's a char*.
中文字幕
Let's go ahead and take a quick break here for five minutes,
and we'll come back and dive in more.
中文字幕
All right.
So we are back, and let's go ahead and simplify this now,
中文字幕
as our tendency has been.
It's kind of a bunch of code, but I think
中文字幕
we can make this a little tighter.
But rather than type this one out manually,
中文字幕
let me go ahead and just open one of our pre-made examples
from today, which is all in the course's website, called compare4.
中文字幕
And you'll see in compare4, that's it.
I only have a main function this time.
中文字幕
I've gotten rid of my compare_strings function because you know what?
I seem to be using something instead.
中文字幕
What function did I apparently deploy?
Yeah, S-T-R-C-M-P, or someone with pronounce it,
中文字幕
just str compare or strcmp.
So this, like strlen, also succinctly named,
中文字幕
is just a function that's actually declared
in one of our familiar libraries up top, string.h,
中文字幕
and it turns out if you look in the man page, so to speak,
by typing man strcmp, or if you go to CS50 reference and actually
中文字幕
look at the less comfortable description of the function there,
this is just a function whose sole purpose in life
中文字幕
is to compare strings for you.
But it's a little different in behavior because it's
中文字幕
a little fancier than the one I just wrote.
Let me zoom in on this, and you'll see that line 14 here, I'm
中文字幕
not quite treating it in the same way.
My logic is ever so slightly different.
中文字幕
What am I actually checking for in my Boolean expression this time?
Yeah, which is a little weird.
中文字幕
I'm checking explicitly-- if strcmp's return value equal-equal to 0.
Before I just said, if compare_strings s comma
中文字幕
t, because I was expecting back a bool-- true or false. strcmp, kind of weird,
acts the opposite way.
中文字幕
It turns out that strcmp doesn't return true and false.
If you read its documentation, it returns 0 if the strings are equal,
中文字幕
but super conveniently, it returns a positive value
if s is supposed to come before t, and it returns a negative value
中文字幕
if s is supposed to come after t alphabetically.
So it turns out that you can use strcmp not just to compare for equality,
中文字幕
but inequality--
less than or equal--
中文字幕
less than or greater than, so to speak, alphabetically,
or in ASCII order, so to speak.
中文字幕
It will actually compare character by character the ASCII values,
and that will make sure that B comes after A,
中文字幕
and C comes after B, and so forth.
So you can actually use strcmp to like sort a dictionary,
中文字幕
or to sort the contacts in your iPhone or your Android phone.
So long story short, this is a function we can use,
中文字幕
we don't have to reinvent this wheel, and thus, we have no more code
even after this.
中文字幕
We just have to use it correctly, and there, the documentation
is your friend.
中文字幕
So if I run this program it's going to work exactly the same way,
but let me go ahead and point out some flaws.
中文字幕
It turns out all this time, I've been a little lazy with my error checking--
checking for errors.
中文字幕
There's a whole bunch of things that can go wrong in week 1 of CS50
that we just kind of turn a blind eye to, because it would just
中文字幕
bloat our code, make it longer and sort of less interesting and fun to write
and less comprehensible.
中文字幕
But today, now that we know what's actually going on,
we can begin to ask some additional questions
中文字幕
and make our code stronger, more robust so
that nothing does, in fact, go wrong.
中文字幕
Turns out, if you read the documentation for get_string in the man page
or in CS50 reference, turns out get_string
中文字幕
does return a string-- uh, not really.
It returns the address of a string.
中文字幕
Uh, not really.
It returns the address of the first byte of a string, technically.
中文字幕
But if something goes wrong, it returns a special character called null.
Not to be confused with NUL, it returns a special address called null--
中文字幕
left hand wasn't talking to right hand decades ago.
So null, N-U-L-L, just means the address 0, which nothing should ever live at.
中文字幕
It's just a bogus, invalid address.
Insofar as get_string returns the address of a string in memory,
中文字幕
like 100 for Brian or 900 for Veronica, if get_string ever
runs into a problem and just something goes wrong with the computer,
中文字幕
if it ever returns 0, specifically 0, a.k.a.
null-- N-U-L-L, then you can detect that something has gone wrong.
中文字幕
So to do that, and it's going to get a little tedious,
but it's nonetheless the right thing to do,
中文字幕
I need to be a little more defensive.
If s equals-equals null, otherwise known as 0, otherwise known as 0x0,
中文字幕
but I'll write it conventionally like this,
I'm going to go ahead and return 1 as my exit code.
中文字幕
If t equals-equals null, I'm going to go ahead and return 1 as my exit code,
or I could return 2 or 3--
中文字幕
I just need to return some value to signal to the computer
that something went wrong, but by default we'll
中文字幕
just return 1 whenever something goes wrong, but if all went well,
I'm going to go ahead and return 0.
中文字幕
So recall again from last week, and we didn't spend a huge amount of time
on this--
中文字幕
main itself can return values.
By default, ever since week 1, if you don't return anything,
中文字幕
main is automatically and secretly returning 0 for you because 0 is good.
The reason for 0 is because there's only one 0 in the world, obviously,
中文字幕
but there is an infinite number to the left
and there's an infinite number of the right, negative and positive.
中文字幕
That's great, because as you've already experienced in the past few weeks,
it feels like there's an infinite number of things that can go wrong when you're
中文字幕
writing even the shortest of programs.
So that means we have a lot of numbers we can assign to error codes,
中文字幕
so to speak.
Now I don't really care what the error codes are,
中文字幕
so I'm just going to adopt the human convention at the moment--
if anything goes wrong, returns anything other than 0.
中文字幕
And so I'm going to return 1 up here, but if nothing goes wrong, return 0.
The point here is that by adding these three lines here and these three
中文字幕
lines here, I'm going to avoid what's called
a segmentation fault or segfault. Did any of you
中文字幕
encounter this cryptic error?
OK.
中文字幕
So a decent number of you, and if you probably had no idea what that means,
but starting today you will a bit more, and in the weeks to come,
中文字幕
you'll understand even more.
Segmentation fault means you touched memory you should not have.
中文字幕
Or something went wrong and you did not detect it.
It's kind of a catch-all phrase for memory-related problems.
中文字幕
This helps ward off those kinds of errors.
It's not the only way, but it's one such way.
中文字幕
So starting today with problems set programs and anything
you write in the course, you always want to be thinking about,
中文字幕
even if you go back and add it later, could this go wrong?
Could this go wrong?
中文字幕
And just add some additional ifs and else-ifs
and handle those situations so that your program doesn't just crash on you
中文字幕
or segfault or surprise someone who's actually using it.
All right, let's take a look at one final example,
中文字幕
because frankly this is a little tedious.
I'm going to go ahead and open up--
中文字幕
and this file can be found in compare5.c.
Let me go ahead and save this so that we have it-- compare5.c.
中文字幕
I'm going to make one final comparison example.
I'm going to save this as compare6.c.
中文字幕
Turns out that humans like their succinctness.
And null, because it is technically the 0 address,
中文字幕
you can actually be a little clever.
If not s and if not t is a sufficient way to express those same things.
中文字幕
Because what does the bang do?
The exclamation point in code if you recall?
中文字幕
It inverts something.
So like if this is saying, if s is not 0, a.k.a., if s not null, or rather--
中文字幕
if-- now I'm getting confused.
Yes.
中文字幕
If I had just said, if s, then it's a valid address
and I should go on with my business.
中文字幕
But if it's not s or if s is null, I want
to go ahead and return 1 because there's an error, and down here too.
中文字幕
So any time you're checking whether something equals null,
you can make it more succinct by just saying if not s; if it's null,
中文字幕
return 1.
If it's null, return 1.
中文字幕
It's just syntactic shorthand.
Phew!
中文字幕
I had to think about that one.
Any questions?
中文字幕
Why does [INAUDIBLE] will store some [INAUDIBLE]
Correct.
中文字幕
You are storing an address, but if that address is 0.
Saying if it's not 0, 0 is like false, so not false means true,
中文字幕
and so it has the effect of inverting the logic.
That's all.
中文字幕
Anytime you use a bang or exclamation point, it changes a 0 to non-0--
, but even--
中文字幕
I don't understand why [INAUDIBLE] implies that it's [INAUDIBLE]..
So you can think about it this way.
中文字幕
If s-- previously we had this.
If s equals-equals null is like saying if s literally equals 0.
中文字幕
And you can kind of think of that informally as
if s doesn't have a valid pointer--
中文字幕
0 is not a valid point or it's not a valid address by definition.
100 is valid, 900 is valid, 0 is not valid just by a human convention.
中文字幕
So this is like saying, if s does not have a value, that's valid.
So the way to succinctly say that, if not s,
中文字幕
and it's just shorthand for that is another way to think about it.
All right, so let's take a look at a very different program,
中文字幕
but that reveals the same kind of issue as follows.
I'm going to go ahead and open up an example called
中文字幕
copy0, whose purpose in life hopefully is to copy a string.
So notice that in my program here, which I
中文字幕
wrote in advance, I'm getting a string from the user on line 11,
and I'm storing it in a string called s.
中文字幕
I could change this to char* now, but we know what it is.
And I'm going to go ahead and copy the string's address from s into t.
中文字幕
And then I'm going to say, if the length of t is greater than 0,
then go ahead and just capitalize the first character.
中文字幕
So it's a little cryptic, but you might have
done something kind of like this with Caesar and with recent string
中文字幕
manipulation.
This is just making sure, do I have at least one character?
中文字幕
And if so, first character is t bracket 0, as you recall.
toupper is a function in ctype.h from last week
中文字幕
that just capitalizes this letter.
So this one line of code, 19, just capitalizes the first letter
中文字幕
in t, that's it.
And then at the very end we just print out what s is and print out what t is.
中文字幕
That's all.
So this program just copies s into t, capitalizes t, and that's it.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and make copy0.
This is in our code from today.
中文字幕
So I'm going to do cd sc3, because I already wrote it in that directory.
make copy0.
中文字幕
Went well. ./copy0.
Let's go ahead and type in tj again in lowercase.
中文字幕
Enter.
Huh.
中文字幕
TJ, TJ-- both are capitalized.
All right, maybe it's just a weird thing with initials.
中文字幕
So let's just do Veronica, all lowercase.
Huh, that's definitely capital.
中文字幕
Let's do even more obvious difference, Brian where
the B's really going to look different.
中文字幕
Yet I'm only capitalizing t.
Well let's consider what's actually going on here.
中文字幕
In this case, when I'm getting a string from the user, s and t, and I type in,
for instance, brian in all lowercase, backslash 0, this, of course,
中文字幕
is just an array underneath the hood.
This is taking up six bytes here.
中文字幕
And when I store in s, s is a string.
So you know what?
中文字幕
We didn't do this before.
Let me actually create a variable, a chunk of memory for s and call it s.
中文字幕
And suppose Brian is just where he was before--
100, 101, 102, 103, 104, and 105.
中文字幕
So if I do s equals get_string and get_string returns Brian,
what do I write in the box called s?
中文字幕
Yeah, just 100, right?
This is all that's been going on all this time
中文字幕
even though we didn't talk about it at this level.
And actually, it turns out-- pointer actually can be used pictorially.
中文字幕
If you actually prefer to think about a pointer as being an address
or like kind of a map that leads you somewhere, another way a human
中文字幕
would typically draw a pointer-- because honestly,
who really cares that Brian is at address 100?
中文字幕
Like that is way too low level, that's week 0 stuff.
He's just pointing there.
中文字幕
So s is a pointer to that chunk of memory.
It happens to be 100, whatever, the arrow is how you would literally
中文字幕
point at the chunk of memory if you were drawing this on some notes.
So that, too, is correct.
中文字幕
So the problem arises here with that line of code.
When I actually try to copy s and store in t, think about what's going on.
中文字幕
The right-hand side is just s's value, which happens to be 100.
The left-hand side is just saying, hey computer, give me
中文字幕
another variable, first string, and call it t.
So that's like saying, hey, computer, give me another chunk of memory,
中文字幕
call it t, and then store s in it.
But what does it mean to store s?
中文字幕
Well what is s's value at this point in time?
It's the pointer to Brian, or it's technically--
中文字幕
I'll write both just for thoroughness-- it's literally the number 100.
So if you do t equals s, that is like saying put 100 there too,
中文字幕
and pictorially that's like saying this.
So at this point in the story, when I copy s into t,
中文字幕
the computer took me literally.
It did copy s into t, but what is s?
中文字幕
It's just the address.
It is not B-R-I-A-N backslash 0, it's just the address.
中文字幕
So when I then say, t bracket 0 gets toupper--
so let's look at this line of code.
中文字幕
The one line of code here that's highlighted,
when I say go to the 0th character of t and store
中文字幕
the uppercase version of that same character, you just follow the arrows.
If you ever played chutes and ladders as a kid,
中文字幕
you just kind of follow the arrow, see where you end up.
t bracket 0 is this location here, because again,
中文字幕
if this is a chunk of memory, per last week it's an array,
so you can also think of this as being bracket 0, this is bracket 1,
中文字幕
this is bracket 2, and so forth.
So it's just an array.
中文字幕
So t bracket 0 is lowercase b, and toupper of lowercase b,
of course, changes this little b to a B. But now
中文字幕
both s and t are still pointing at the same chunk of memory,
so of course s and t are both going to be Bryan capitalized,
中文字幕
or TJ too in my first example.
Any questions then on what we just did and why that happens?
中文字幕
All right, so intuitively what's the fix?
Doesn't matter if you've no idea how to code it,
中文字幕
like what do we have to do to fundamentally copy a string, not
an address?
中文字幕
Create a new what?
AUDIENCE: Basically create the [INAUDIBLE]..
中文字幕
Yeah.
Create the same string in a new chunk of memory.
中文字幕
What I really need to do is allocate or give myself
a bunch of more memory that's just as big as Brian,
中文字幕
including his backslash 0.
And then logically I just need to copy every character into that.
中文字幕
So if I go back to my original when it was a lowercase b,
I need to make a copy logically by using a for loop or a while loop
中文字幕
or whatever you prefer--
B-R-I-A-N backslash 0, so that when I copy the string and then store it in t,
中文字幕
It's not actually copying literally s.
And let's suppose that he ends up at location 300 just arbitrarily--
中文字幕
just making up easy numbers.
t now stores 300, points here.
中文字幕
So when I execute this line in this version of the story, t bracket 0
gets toupper, what am I actually doing?
中文字幕
I'm following a different arrow this time
because I gave myself a different chunk of memory, capitalizing this Brian,
中文字幕
thereby hopefully fixing the bug, albeit verbally only.
So how do we do this in code?
中文字幕
We need to do exactly that.
We need to give ourself some more memory,
中文字幕
so let's introduce one other feature of C. In copy1.c,
we see the solution to this problem.
中文字幕
Notice at the top I'm doing things a little lower level-- oop, surprise.
Notice in this version of the code, copy1.c,
中文字幕
see I've started off almost the same, but just to be super clear,
I'm just using char*.
中文字幕
I don't want any magic, so there's no string,
there's no training wheels here.
中文字幕
But this logically is the exact same as before--
plus the error-checking.
中文字幕
This line is new.
And it looks a little funky, but let's see what's going on.
中文字幕
And this line of code here, what am I doing?
The left-hand side, that's shorter, let's start with the easier one.
中文字幕
Char* t, just in layman's terms, what does that expression do? char*?
Hey computer, do what?
中文字幕
What's that?
Not quite yet.
中文字幕
Different formulation.
Hey computer, give me--
中文字幕
not quite.
Be more precise?
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: An array?
Not quite an array, just this part.
中文字幕
So let me hide all this.
If the star wasn't there--
中文字幕
I can't really do this very well.
So this-- yeah?
中文字幕
character?
Good, I'll take that.
中文字幕
So hey computer, give me a pointer to a character.
Or even more low level, hey computer, give me
中文字幕
a chunk of memory in which I can store the address of a character.
I mean, it is that mundane.
中文字幕
Draw a box on the screen, call it s-- or rather,
call it t, but just give me space for a pointer, as you said.
中文字幕
So that's all that's doing.
It's drawing a box on the screen and calling it t, and it's currently empty.
中文字幕
Now let's look at the scarier part on the right-hand side.
malloc, new function today.
中文字幕
Stands for memory allocates.
It's very cryptic-sounding, but it just means give me a chunk of memory.
中文字幕
It says exactly what you said in functional terms.
Then it just needs you to answer one question--
中文字幕
OK, how much memory do you want?
How many bytes do you want?
中文字幕
And now maybe the math, even though cryptic at first glance, makes sense.
Get the string length of s, add 1, and then multiply it
中文字幕
by the size of a character.
And we've not seen this before. sizeof literally does that.
中文字幕
It tells you how many bytes is a char.
Happens to be 1, and in fact, that's defined.
中文字幕
So if we simplify this in C, the char is always 1 byte,
so this is equivalent to just multiplying by 1.
中文字幕
And obviously mathematically that's a waste of time,
so we can whittle this down to be even simpler.
中文字幕
I was just being thorough.
So now, hey computer, allocate me this many bytes of memory.
中文字幕
Why is it plus 1?
AUDIENCE: You need the null character.
中文字幕
I need that null character.
Brian is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 as he said, but I need the sixth for his null character,
中文字幕
and I just know that's going to be there.
So at this point in the story, what has happened?
中文字幕
All that malloc does is it gives me this box of memory
containing room for as many bytes are in Brian's name.
中文字幕
But it doesn't fill them just yet.
Now I need to logically fill those bytes with Brian's actual name.
中文字幕
So if we scroll down to my for loop here,
we can actually copy the string into that space.
中文字幕
And it's a little long, the expression, but nothing new here.
Initialize i to 0, n to the length of s, i is less than or equal to n--
中文字幕
we'll come back to that, i++.
So it's just a pretty standard for loop.
中文字幕
Then copy the i-th character of s into the i-th character of t.
The only thing that's making me a little nervous honestly is this thing here.
中文字幕
Like I feel like every time we do less than or equal to,
we create a bug like last week.
中文字幕
But this is correct, why?
Why do I want to go up to and through the length of this?
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: Is it the null character that adds--
Exactly.
中文字幕
Because of the null character.
I actually don't want to stop at the strlen of s, so I could change this.
中文字幕
If you're just more comfortable using less than, because you just
got your mind wrapped around why we do that in the first place, that's fine,
中文字幕
we just need to do this instead.
So this is mathematically-- if you go to strlen plus 1, the same thing
中文字幕
as not doing that math but just going one step further.
Just whatever you want to think about it is fine.
中文字幕
However you want to think about it is fine.
OK, and then lastly, just a quick check, is the length
中文字幕
of t at least one or more characters?
Because otherwise there's nothing to capitalize, and if so,
中文字幕
go ahead and do it.
So if I now run this example, make-- oop, let me save it.
中文字幕
make copy1, that compiled.
./copy1, now let's type in tj, tj in lowercase comes back,
中文字幕
but now t is capitalized.
And let's go ahead and do Brian's name in all lowercase, only one of them
中文字幕
is now capitalized.
So does that make sense what's now happened?
中文字幕
All right.
So where can we go with this?
中文字幕
Well it turns out-- let me open up one final example here,
because honestly, that's incredibly tedious,
中文字幕
and no one's ever going to want to copy strings if you
have to go through all of that work.
中文字幕
Turns out that store copy exists.
So when in doubt, check the man page.
中文字幕
When in doubt, check CS50 reference.
Does the function exist somewhere related
中文字幕
to some keywords you have in mind?
Like string copy, see if something comes back.
中文字幕
And indeed, we've had strlen, we've had strcmp, we now have strcpy,
and if you read the documentation, this is deliberately reversed like this.
中文字幕
The destination is this variable, the source or the origin string
is this one, and it copies from one end to the other,
中文字幕
and then I don't need that for loop.
It just saves me a few lines of code.
中文字幕
All right.
So let's take off one other detail here.
中文字幕
Oh, and you'll notice, actually, let me make one fix, one fix here.
It turns out that what I'm doing here is a little lazy.
中文字幕
It turns out that malloc does have an opposite.
So anytime you allocate memory, technically
中文字幕
you should also be freeing that memory.
And so C allows you to ask the computer for as much memory as you want,
中文字幕
but if you never give it back, have you ever experienced on your own Mac or PC,
like after your computer's been running a while
中文字幕
or using some new or bloated program like a browser,
it gets slower and slower and slower?
中文字幕
And in the worse case it just freezes or hangs or something?
It is quite possible that that program simply-- was made by humans,
中文字幕
of course--
just has a memory leak.
中文字幕
So some human wrote one or more lines of code that uses malloc
or some equivalent in another language that just kept allocating memory
中文字幕
for the user's input.
You're visiting one web page, two web pages,
中文字幕
that requires memory whatever the program is.
And if that human never calls the opposite of allocate-- deallocate,
中文字幕
otherwise known as free, you're never giving the memory back
to the operating system.
中文字幕
So it gets slower and slower because it's running lower and lower and lower
on memory, and it might have to move some things around
中文字幕
to make room for things, that's what's called a memory leak.
And so indeed, in this program, I should actually improve this a little bit.
中文字幕
If I go back into this version here and line 18, recall,
I allocated this memory just to make my copy,
中文字幕
the very last thing I should actually do in this program
is this line here-- free.
中文字幕
You don't have to tell the computer how many bytes you want to free,
it will remember for you so long as you're just pass in the pointer--
中文字幕
the variable that's storing the address of the chunk of memory
that you allocated.
中文字幕
All right.
So let's now see why we've been using get_string,
中文字幕
since it's not just to kind of simplify the code,
it's also to defend against some very easy problems.
中文字幕
Here is a program called scanf0--
scanned formatted text, another arcane-sounding function,
中文字幕
but it's pretty straightforward.
This program simply gets in from the user using scanf.
中文字幕
Up until now for the past three weeks, you've used get_int.
So this is an alternative to get_int that you could
中文字幕
have started using a few weeks ago.
Give me an int called x, print out x colon whatever--
中文字幕
that's just the prompt to the user.
scanf %i, &x;, whatever that is, and then print out x's value using %i.
中文字幕
So what's going on here?
Now today we can actually start to wrap our minds around what get_int actually
中文字幕
does.
This is effectively get_int.
中文字幕
If you actually look at the source code for get_int, it's a little fancier.
But in essence, what get_int does is it declares a variable called x,
中文字幕
and it doesn't put anything there, because that's
supposed to come from you, the human.
中文字幕
It then prompts you for whatever string you pass to get_int,
so those are the first two lines.
中文字幕
And this is the only weird-looking one.
Scanf is like the opposite of printf.
中文字幕
You still use a formatted string-- %s, %i, %f or whatever,
but you're not going to output this, you're going to input this from
中文字幕
the human's keyboard.
And %x is the opposite of--
中文字幕
is the special symbol in C that says, go ahead and get me the address of x.
So don't pass in x, give me the address of x.
中文字幕
Now why is that?
We'll see, but this is the way where you can tell the computer,
中文字幕
I've made a variable for you called x, here is where it is.
It's a treasure map that leads you to x, go put a value here for me.
中文字幕
And so the end result is that we do, in fact, end up getting an int.
If I do make scanf0, and then ./scanf0, I'll type in 42, all right?
中文字幕
It's not an interesting program, it just spits back out what I got,
but that's literally all that get_int, of course,
中文字幕
is doing if you then print out the value.
So if I stipulate this is correct, this is how you get an int from the user,
中文字幕
but honestly, the reason we don't do this in week 1 of the course is like,
my God, we just took the fun out of even getting a simple number from the user
中文字幕
by using these lines of code and whoever knows
what this symbol is-- we don't want you to think about that,
中文字幕
we want you to just get an int.
But today those training wheels are off, but we're
中文字幕
going to run into a problem super fast.
Let's try the same thing with a string.
中文字幕
If I were to do this, you would think that the result is the same.
Or let's just do it as char*.
中文字幕
But there's going to be one tweak.
If I go ahead and give myself space for the address of a character,
中文字幕
I don't need to use the ampersand now, because scanf
does need to be told where the chunk of memory is,
中文字幕
but it's already an address, so I don't need the ampersand here.
Recall earlier, I declared int x, which was just an int.
中文字幕
%x gets the address of that int.
Here, I'm saying from the get-go, get me the address of a char.
中文字幕
I don't need the ampersand cause I already have the address of a char
by definition of that star symbol.
中文字幕
So what's going on here?
Let me see now.
中文字幕
If I run scanf1, what happens?
So make scanf1 and--
中文字幕
oh, let's see.
Here's a warning I'm getting.
中文字幕
Variable s is uninitialized when used here.
All right, that's fine.
中文字幕
It wants me to initialize it because this is a very common mistake.
Those of you who alluded to segmentation faults
中文字幕
earlier might have encountered something similar in spirit to this.
So that squelched that error.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and run scanf1.
All right, here we go, TJ.
中文字幕
Hmm.
That is not your name, but OK.
中文字幕
It didn't crash at least, it's just a little weird.
David.
中文字幕
Null, OK, that's a little weird.
Let's go ahead and do this again.
中文字幕
Let's type in a really long name.
Enter.
中文字幕
Dammit, that didn't work.
So let's try an even longer name.
中文字幕
I'm hitting paste a lot.
OK-- dammit.
中文字幕
Too many times.
Command not found, that's definitely not a command.
中文字幕
Wow, OK.
Well that's interesting.
中文字幕
Oh, there it is.
Null, same thing.
中文字幕
OK, so what's actually going on?
Well null, which is all lowercase here, which
中文字幕
is this kind of an aesthetic thing, well it's not working.
It's not working.
中文字幕
Well what am I actually doing?
In that first line of code, when I say give me s to be a char*,
中文字幕
otherwise known as a string, all that's doing is allocating this.
And it's technically the size of a pointer.
中文字幕
A pointer, we never mentioned this before, but now we can.
Turns out it is 64 bits or 8 bytes.
中文字幕
8 bits is 1 bytes, so a pointer is by definition on many computers these
days-- most of your Macs, most of your PCs, the IDE, the Sandbox, the Lab--
中文字幕
is 64-bit.
So that just means there's 64 bits here, but we initialized it to null,
中文字幕
so that just means there's 64 0's here, dot-dot-dot.
But when I get a string using scanf, what
中文字幕
I'm telling the computer to do with this line of code here,
notice, is hey computer, go to that address and put a string there.
中文字幕
So what's actually happening?
It turns out that there's just not enough room to type in TJ.
中文字幕
There's not enough room--
that's a bit of a white lie, because we could fit you in 64 bits,
中文字幕
but there's not enough room to type in the long sentence or paragraph of text
I did, right?
中文字幕
What did we not do?
We didn't allocate any space over here.
中文字幕
All we allocated space for was the address.
And so every time I use scanf saying, get me a string and put it here,
中文字幕
there's nowhere to put it.
And so the value just very defensively says, no, like no,
中文字幕
cannot store this anywhere for you.
So I actually need to be a little smarter about this.
中文字幕
I actually need to get myself some space so that I can actually store something
in the right place.
中文字幕
Let's do that.
Let me go ahead and create a new program.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead and call this scanf2.
We need a little secret code to remind me of that.
中文字幕
Oh, wrong file name.
So I'm gone ahead and create a file called scanf2.
中文字幕
scanf2.c.
And I'm going to quickly recreate this stdio.h, int main void,
中文字幕
and then down here I'm going to go ahead and-- you know what?
Instead of a string s, which I know today to be a char* s,
中文字幕
what is this string really?
Well you said it earlier.
中文字幕
What is this string?
It's an array of characters.
中文字幕
Let me take you literally.
Just give me an array of let's say five characters.
中文字幕
The D-A-V-I-D, or one more, that's fine, just enough for my backslash 0.
Let me just create a string-- really low level,
中文字幕
but this time give myself the chunk of memory.
I don't want just the address of a character,
中文字幕
I want the actual characters themselves.
Let me go ahead and just prompt the human for their string with s,
中文字幕
just like before.
Then let me call scanf and get a string from the user using %s and then pass
中文字幕
in s.
And here's a little trick.
中文字幕
It turns out that because a string is really just an array,
but a string is also just a pointer, you can actually treat
中文字幕
an array as though it is a pointer--
an address.
中文字幕
And so even though this is a char* array, this is OK.
This is the equivalent in this context to being just the address of a string.
中文字幕
Because strings are arrays, arrays can be treated as pointers as of now.
And then let me go ahead and just print out whatever the human typed in.
中文字幕
S is actually this.
Pass in s;, save.
中文字幕
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: So [INAUDIBLE] char*?
中文字幕
At this point it would be redundant to do char*,
because I literally want for this story six characters.
中文字幕
I want space, rather, for six characters.
So this is kind of week 2 stuff now, there's no pointers involved.
中文字幕
But again, just showing the equivalence of these ideas for now.
So if I now go into this, and this is in my other directory at the moment,
中文字幕
make scanf2, Enter, ./scanf2, s is going to type in--
I'll type in my name, I know I can fit that, we're back in business.
中文字幕
Like now it's working because I didn't just create the address for a string,
I created the space for the string.
中文字幕
But let me get a little dangerous--
David Malan?
中文字幕
OK, that kind of worked out OK.
David Malan or some really long other name?
中文字幕
OK, that worked out too.
Let me go ahead and run it again.
中文字幕
Let me try that really long string again, see what happens.
I know this didn't work very well last time.
中文字幕
All right, done.
Ooh, OK.
中文字幕
So now I'm in the club of those of you who have had segmentation faults.
So let's understand what's going on here.
中文字幕
Segmentation fault a moment ago I claimed
was touching a segment, a chunk of memory that's not your own.
中文字幕
So just happened?
Well with this simple program, I told the computer, hey computer,
中文字幕
give me room for six characters, give me six bytes.
With the scanf line, I'm telling the computer, put the following user
中文字幕
input at that location, in that array of characters.
D-A-V-I-D backslash 0 fit.
中文字幕
David Malan didn't really, but it didn't seem to be a huge deal.
David Malan or some really long other name, also didn't crash the computer.
中文字幕
But that's because unbeknownst to us, usually when you ask for six bytes,
the computer is kind of sort of-- it's giving you a few extras.
中文字幕
It's not safe to use them, but it gives you enough
that you're not going to necessarily see a problem like a segmentation fault.
中文字幕
But it only allocates a few extra bytes typically,
so if you really keep pasting in long, long, long, long lines of text,
中文字幕
eventually you're going exceed not only those six
bytes, but well past the special--
中文字幕
the secret bytes that you got back that you shouldn't be using anyway,
and that point the computer just gives up and says,
中文字幕
you are touching memory you shouldn't, a.k.a.
segmentation fault.
中文字幕
if the computer gives you
a few extra bytes, then why isn't it printing any of the other stuff?
中文字幕
After you said [INAUDIBLE] it just printed David.
Really good question.
中文字幕
So even though I'm getting these sort of extra bytes,
why am I not seeing them after D-A-V-I-D?
中文字幕
I'm probably getting lucky.
Long story short, when you first run a program,
中文字幕
much of the memory that your program has access to is by default initialized
to 0's.
中文字幕
0 is the same thing as backslash 0, and so I'm getting lucky.
When I had D-A-V-I-D and then excess space in that array,
中文字幕
a lot of them are initialized as 0's already,
and the string is getting secretly terminated for me.
中文字幕
Or the better answer is, it's undefined behavior.
Like you should not touch memory that is not your own.
中文字幕
What happens after that is your risk alone.
But that's a conjecture as to why that's happening.
中文字幕
All right, so what is the fundamental feature than get_int
is providing for us?
中文字幕
All of this time get_int has actually been dealing
with all of this headache for us.
中文字幕
I mean honestly, even I'm getting bored like thinking about, talking
about how you just get a damn string from the user,
中文字幕
because you need to figure out, well how many bytes do you need?
And what if the human types in one more bite than you were expecting?
中文字幕
Then you need to do a switcheroo and get more memory.
get_string is doing all of this headache for us.
中文字幕
And that's not to say you need to use it forever,
there are indeed training wheels, but that's
中文字幕
just because when you're using C or a lot of programming languages,
the computer will only do what you tell it to do.
中文字幕
And it turns out that even asking the user for input,
if you don't know how many characters he or she is
中文字幕
going to type in from the get-go, you have to deal with it.
And so underneath the hood-- and you're welcome to take a look at the source
中文字幕
code for CS50's library, which I'll post on the home page later today,
it turns out that with the way we're doing get_string is taking baby steps.
中文字幕
We literally like get one character at a time
from the user, kind of building the road as we go.
中文字幕
And if we don't have enough space, we ask the computer,
give me some more bytes so I can get more bytes,
中文字幕
and we just get one character at a time so
that we can handle the user maliciously or accidentally typing in way
中文字幕
more input than we actually expect.
So let's contextualize all of this then.
中文字幕
Recall that we've been drawing these pictures the past couple of weeks.
Let's just make this super clear as to what's been going on.
中文字幕
This is a memory module in a computer.
It's just a green board, it's way blown out of scale here,
中文字幕
it's easily like yea big inside of your Mac or PC laptop or desktop,
though can vary in size.
中文字幕
One of these black chips is the actual memory or the bytes
to which we've been referring.
中文字幕
And if we zoom in on that, recall that I proposed last week
that you can just think about this as like a grid, an array.
中文字幕
And it doesn't have to be rectangular, this is just an artist's rendition,
but each of those squares represents, we claimed, a byte.
中文字幕
And each of those bytes can be addressed in some way with a number.
And that number is just its location, otherwise known as an address.
中文字幕
We can actually see this, it turns out, as follows.
Let me go ahead and open up this example here.
中文字幕
Or actually, you know, let's just write this one from scratch.
Let me write a program called addresses.c.
中文字幕
And that's going to use our old friends, the CS50 library and stdio.h and int
main void.
中文字幕
And let me go ahead and just do this.
I'm going to go ahead and get a string--
中文字幕
you know what?
No more string. char* from the user, get_string, ask the user for s.
中文字幕
And we get another string, a.k.a.
char*, get_string, call it t from the user.
中文字幕
And then, I want to print out not the strings, which I used to do like this,
printing out s.
中文字幕
I want to print out the pointer that s really is, that is the address.
Turns out %p for pointer will print out not the string at that memory location,
中文字幕
it will print the actual memory location for you of s.
And I can do the same thing here, %p, backslash 0, paste in t.
中文字幕
And just so I know which is which, let me just prefix it
with some text-- s colon and t colon.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead now down here and do make addresses.
Oh, I messed up, missed a semi-colon.
中文字幕
Let me do this again.
make addresses.
中文字幕
And get rid of this.
That compiled OK, ./addresses, and here we go.
中文字幕
Let's type in-- let's do Brian and Veronica like before.
Enter.
中文字幕
And this is a little funky, but it turns out the IDE in your Macs
and your PCs have a lot of memory.
中文字幕
So this is the address.
It's not quite as small as 100, it's not quite as small as 900.
中文字幕
It's actually kind of big.
It's 2331010 with this weird 0x.
中文字幕
Well it turns out, this is just a human convention.
In week 0 we talked about decimal and all of us
中文字幕
grew up with decimal, 10 digits from 0 to 9.
Talked a little bit about binary 0's and 1's.
中文字幕
Turns out there's an infinite number of base systems--
decimal/dec, binary/bi are just two of those infinite number of possibilities.
中文字幕
Turns out there's another one that's super common called hexadecimal.
Hexa meaning 16 in this case.
中文字幕
So base-16 actually has 16 letters in its alphabet.
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, a, b, c, d, e, f.
中文字幕
So it turns out that base systems that need to count higher than 10 characters
just start using letters of the alphabet by convention.
中文字幕
Humans just decided this.
So we're getting just numbers in this case,
中文字幕
but if these addresses were even bigger, we
might actually see some alphabetical letters between a and f there.
中文字幕
And frankly I don't know what address this is,
but Google's usually pretty good at this stuff,
中文字幕
so let me actually open up another browser window.
So Google is your friend when it comes to this stuff, so let me actually open up another browser window.
中文字幕
So Google is your friend when it comes to this stuff,
or any number of calculators.
中文字幕
0x2331010 in decimal please.
And Google has translated that.
中文字幕
So Brian, I-- kind of under a bit earlier.
He is not at address location 0, he's actually
中文字幕
in the 36 millionth byte inside of my computer
right now, location 36,900,880.
中文字幕
So a little higher address than 100.
And then Veronica, if you really want to get into the weeds here,
中文字幕
we can say "in decimal," let Google translate that for us.
She's at location 36,900,944.
中文字幕
Why?
Who cares?
中文字幕
The computer is managing all of this for us, but when get_string used malloc,
these are literally the numbers that were being returned saying,
中文字幕
you may use this chunk of memory.
And why did humans use hexadecimal?
中文字幕
Like it's just slightly more compact to say 0x2331050, then 36900944--
like you just save a few digits, so it's just conventional.
中文字幕
That's all, there's no magic there.
But, recall earlier.
中文字幕
Do you recall that when I had the debugger open earlier,
you saw next to my name variable a value that was cryptically 0x0?
中文字幕
Then there was another value that I don't recall--
0x-something?
中文字幕
That was just the numeric address of my name in hexadecimal.
And 0x0 is just the technical address being used by null.
中文字幕
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: You said the address printed out was [INAUDIBLE] x of the variable s
中文字幕
and--
Sorry, could you say that again?
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: You said the address printed out on the screen was an x,
but x is [INAUDIBLE]
中文字幕
Ah, I should've clarified.
0x, humans years ago decided anytime you see anything
中文字幕
with 0x, that means whatever comes next is hexadecimal.
Just the convention.
中文字幕
It's also common too if it starts with a 0, it's an octal, which is base-8.
If you see a lowercase b at the end, it means binary.
中文字幕
So humans have just come up with symbology
as to kind of communicate this to readers, that's all.
中文字幕
Not part of the value.
So turns out that we can actually do this math ourselves.
中文字幕
And we won't really get into the weeds of this
because it's not a particularly useful life
中文字幕
skill, to be able to convert to various base systems,
but let's just do one example so that we've seen it.
中文字幕
Just to make clear that there's no magic here,
it's just a different way of thinking about numbers versus grade school.
中文字幕
So if back in the day we had three decimal numbers--
255, 216, and then another 255, if we rewound to week 0,
中文字幕
we could go through the math of converting that to binary.
And even if it might take you a little while, this is the binary equivalent.
中文字幕
And frankly, the first and last are kind of easy.
255 is kind of a special value because with 8 bits, all of which
中文字幕
are 1, that's what gives you 255.
So the only hard one is actually this.
中文字幕
But who cares about the math today.
We know from weeks ago that we can do this if we really tried.
中文字幕
But notice that bytes are eight bits, and of course, eight is a pair of four,
if you will.
中文字幕
Well what's really nice about hexadecimal is that it starts at 0
and ends at f.
中文字幕
And that's 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9--
wait-- yes, that's 10.
中文字幕
OK.
And then a, b, c, d, e, f.
中文字幕
I just held up 16 fingers in total, hence, hexadecimal.
What's nice about base-16 is that how many bits do I need to count from 0 up
中文字幕
to--
one, two, three, four--
中文字幕
15?
Just 4, right?
中文字幕
So if I have all 0 bits, that's 0.
And if I have 4 1-bits, that's--
中文字幕
let's see.
This is an 8 plus 4 plus 2 plus 1 gives me 15.
中文字幕
So long story short, hexadecimal's super convenient because 0 through f
maps wonderfully cleanly to 4 bits.
中文字幕
So it's just a nice way of thinking about the world not in units of 8
but in 4 instead.
中文字幕
So all I did here was I took my values and I just
added a little bit of whitespace to make clear
中文字幕
that 8 bits is like a pair of 4 bits.
It turns out now that 1 1 1 1 is f for the reasons I enumerated earlier.
中文字幕
All 1's is f, otherwise known as 15.
All 1's is again f, otherwise known as 15.
中文字幕
If we did the math, 1 1 0 1 is d, 1 0 0 0 is 8, and then all 1's is f and f.
So long story short, there is a way to convert from decimal
中文字幕
to binary, to hexadecimal, to any number of other base systems.
It all just boils down to what digits you care about.
中文字幕
And the way you write this, to your question earlier,
is by human convention.
中文字幕
Not just FFDAFF, but 0xFF0xD80xFF just because.
Then it's clear to the user what it is.
中文字幕
So a little levity now.
I'm sorry to do this to you, but now you will all hopefully
中文字幕
understand this famous comic.
OK, welcome to that club of people who understand things like this.
中文字幕
So let's now stumble upon just one last problem,
and we'll take it home by putting into the context
中文字幕
a very sexy field of forensics where all of these building blocks
will come into play.
中文字幕
But first let's start with a problem.
Suppose I want to implement a function here called swap whose purpose in life
中文字幕
is just to swap two values, a and b.
I just want to do a switcheroo.
中文字幕
Let's first do this with a sort of mid-lecture snack for at least
one person.
中文字幕
Would anyone be up for--
OK, that was fast.
中文字幕
Volunteering, come on up.
What's your name?
中文字幕
Kelly, all right.
Thank you for volunteering so suddenly.
中文字幕
Kelly, David, nice to meet you.
OK, so very simple task at hand.
中文字幕
I have here two empty cups, and we have some orange juice.
OK, put this in here.
中文字幕
And we've got some milk over here.
That should stand out, very different colors.
中文字幕
OK, I would just like you, Kelly, if you could, swap those two values.
Orange goes into milk, milk goes into orange please.
中文字幕
That is cheating, OK?
No, I mean literally the cups.
中文字幕
I put them in the wrong cup, I prefer my milk
in the other cup and my orange juice in the other cup, I'm sorry.
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: Pour it back in.
No, that is not available to you, OK?
中文字幕
[LAUGHTER]
OK, so you're struggling.
中文字幕
Why are you struggling?
KELLY: Because I'm going to mix them.
中文字幕
And then it won't be the same.
Right.
中文字幕
So I mean obviously, this is kind of a losing proposition.
You can't really do this.
中文字幕
What would make this easier for you besides putting them back
in the bottles?
中文字幕
KELLY: Having another container.
Yeah.
中文字幕
So you need like a temporary storage space for this.
You know, let me--
中文字幕
Tara, can we get some more cups over here?
Ah, this will make it easier.
中文字幕
OK, so if I get you some temporary space--
here you go-- could you solve the problem now please?
中文字幕
Ah, very nice.
A little contamination, but that's OK.
中文字幕
But I need that temporary cup back for Tara.
Yeah, OK.
中文字幕
Thank you.
All right, a round of applause if we could for Kelly here.
中文字幕
[APPLAUSE]
Well here we go.
中文字幕
I'm guessing you don't want warm milk, but orange juice?
OK.
中文字幕
Thank you so much.
All right, so what's the point here?
中文字幕
This is pretty easy.
Like once you have some temporary storage
中文字幕
space-- a variable, if you will, like it's no problem to swap two values.
So let me go ahead and do that as follows.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead and just implement this swap function
and see exactly as Kelly ultimately just implemented it.
中文字幕
If the goal is to swap a and b, I can't just do a complete switcheroo,
it seems.
中文字幕
I need to put one of those values, like the milk, in another container,
and then swap and then swap.
中文字幕
So it takes three steps, not just one.
All right, so I could call this extra variable or cup
中文字幕
that Tara gave us anything we want-- tmp.
So I'm just going to put a in tmp.
中文字幕
Then I'm going to put b in a, because a is now empty.
Then I'm going to put tmp in b, and then I don't really
中文字幕
care what happens to tmp-- indeed, it's just still sitting there,
but the job is now done.
中文字幕
So let's go ahead and see this program in action, because obviously this
should be pretty straightforward.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and open up this program
in the context of a main function so we can actually run it.
中文字幕
In this code here, I'm going to demonstrate it as follows.
Here's my main function.
中文字幕
I'm going to call variable x, give it 1, call variable y,
give it 2, go ahead and just print out just for a quick sanity check--
中文字幕
x is this, y is that.
Then I'm going to call this super simple swap function, x, y.
中文字幕
Then I'm going to print the exact same thing-- x is this, y is that,
just so I can see in those variables--
中文字幕
I could also use debug50, but this is meant to be a complete solution,
I want to see it on the screen.
中文字幕
Here is swap.
I copy-pasted that from before.
中文字幕
This feels like a no-brainer, super straightforward,
let's go into my directory and compile this program, which, slight spoiler,
中文字幕
noswap is the name.
./noswap.
中文字幕
Oof.
Let's zoom in.
中文字幕
Nope, that is not what I intended, right?
I really intended milk to become OJ, OJ to become milk,
中文字幕
or x become y, y become x, this doesn't seem to work.
And again, the only magic is this one call to swap.
中文字幕
All right, maybe it just works some of the time.
So nope, nope-- OK.
中文字幕
Now it's time for the debugger.
I don't understand what's going on in my program,
中文字幕
printf is not really illuminating here.
So let me go ahead and run debug50 ./noswap.
中文字幕
The little debugging panels get opened on the side,
but wait, I need a breakpoint.
中文字幕
I'm going to start a breakpoint at the very top, the first line I care about.
I don't really care about all the stuff at the super top.
中文字幕
Now I'm going to go ahead and rerun debug50 ./noswap, all right?
Now I see over here, the first line 9 is highlighted.
中文字幕
Notice on the right-hand side, and this perhaps
answers by example your question earlier.
中文字幕
x and y conveniently, but just because we're initialized to 0--
not by me, I shouldn't necessarily trust this in all contexts,
中文字幕
but that's why they had values.
They're otherwise known as garbage values, but I got lucky with 0's here.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and step over that line, and if you watch, albeit small,
on the right-hand side, x should suddenly take on a value of 1.
中文字幕
And if I step over one more line, y should take on a value of 2.
OK, so I'm pretty confident the program is thus far correct.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead and step over printf.
And notice the blue terminal window, I see one output.
中文字幕
Now things get interesting.
If I continue stepping over lines, it's just going to finish running
中文字幕
and that's not enough.
So notice this time I'm going to hover over this third icon, Step Into.
中文字幕
Now I can kind of go down the rabbit hole,
so to speak, and go into the swap function, and notice,
中文字幕
the debugger jumps into that other function.
So here now, the context changed.
中文字幕
My local variables are now a, b, and tmp, and this is really weird.
A is 1, b is 2, as expected, because I passed an x, y.
中文字幕
And in the context of this function I'm just calling them a, b because.
But why is tmp 32,767?
中文字幕
It's just because it can't be trusted, it's a garbage value.
If you just give yourself a temporary value, who knows what's in there?
中文字幕
We got lucky and Tara did not have anything in this cup,
but it could have had a garbage value, maybe it had some Pepsi,
中文字幕
and then we would have had to replace that value somehow.
So to be clear, when you declare variables in a program,
中文字幕
quite often they have garbage values, just bogus values--
the 0's and 1's that are there underneath the hood in that chip,
中文字幕
but that you didn't set yourself.
But that's OK, because I'm explicitly in this next line setting tmp equal to a.
中文字幕
So it doesn't matter what its original weird value was, so if I click Next,
tmp is now 1, a.k.a.
中文字幕
a.
Now notice a is going to become b if you watch the right-hand side.
中文字幕
Now I seem to have a is 2, b is 2, which is a little worrisome but not as bad,
because I have that separate variable tmp, so I still have the one around.
中文字幕
So now b is about to become 1, and I've done the switcheroo.
OK, at this point in the story, line 22, my code seems correct.
中文字幕
b has become a, a has become b, and the values are swapped--
and the debugger is confirming that for me visually.
中文字幕
So now, let's do a step and--
dammit.
中文字幕
Lost.
What is going on?
中文字幕
Intuitively?
Even if you've never seen or done this before, like clearly there's a bug.
中文字幕
What is that bug?
What must be happening?
中文字幕
Yeah?
a new value
中文字幕
doesn't have the same address for the first one?
Yeah.
中文字幕
What seems to be happening here is yes, you're passing in x and y
and calling it a and b, but a and b would seem to be copies of x and y.
中文字幕
And I am very successfully, very correctly swapping a and b,
but because they're copies, it has no effect on the original x and y.
中文字幕
So our metaphor here of juice isn't quite apt
because I didn't pass Kelly copies of the OJ and milk,
中文字幕
I handed her the actual OJ and milk and she was able to change the values.
But in the context of C and code, when you pass arguments to a function,
中文字幕
you're passing copies of those arguments to the function.
So intuitively, what is the solution?
中文字幕
We clearly cannot pass from one function to another copies of the values if we
expect the function swap, or a.k.a.
中文字幕
Kelly, to make some useful change for us.
What do we have to pass to the function or to Kelly instead?
中文字幕
The addresses of those values, right?
I told her where the milk and OJ were.
中文字幕
I didn't give her copies of them, I told her, here's the milk,
here's the OJ, swap those.
中文字幕
In this version of the code, I've just said,
here's a copy of x, here's a copy of y, you can call them a and b-- um-mmm.
中文字幕
We need to now use the ampersand or something like that to pass in a map,
if you will.
中文字幕
The treasure map to those values so that swap can change the original values.
And the way we do this is a little weird-looking,
中文字幕
but all we're going to have to do is make a little addition here
that looks as follows.
中文字幕
It's got to look like this instead.
So this is the broken version.
中文字幕
Or broken in that it doesn't have the effect we intend even though it works.
This is what we need to do instead, and it's the last piece
中文字幕
of new symbology for today.
We've seen star in a couple of different places
中文字幕
before, now we're using it in one final context.
When you specify a star here and here in the arguments to a function, that
中文字幕
is just the way you tell the computer, I'm
expecting not an int, but the address of an int.
中文字幕
I'm expecting not an int here, but the address of an int.
So two pointers, two addresses of integers.
中文字幕
Down here, tmp is still just an int.
I don't need to over think tmp, that's just an empty cup.
中文字幕
Give me an integer called tmp from week 1.
But, what do I want to store in tmp?
中文字幕
Both a and b in this version are addresses.
Do I want to remember the address a and the address b?
中文字幕
No, I want to remember the volume of OJ, the volume of milk,
I want to remember 1 and 2, I don't care where in memory they are.
中文字幕
So star in this context, when there's no mention of a data type,
there's just a star and a variable name.
中文字幕
That variable is a pointer and it's not multiplication,
there's no math going on.
中文字幕
That star is the dereference operator that says, go to this address
and get the value there.
中文字幕
So if this address a is at location, I don't know, 100 like Brian was,
and this address b is at location 900 like Veronica was,
中文字幕
*a means go to the 100th byte in memory and get me that value, which is 1.
This means, down here, go to the address b, get me that value at address 900,
中文字幕
which is 2.
And go ahead and store 1 in tmp.
中文字幕
Go ahead and go to that address and put whatever's
at b's address-- so get that address and put it over-- get that address,
中文字幕
get the value, and put it over at that address by dereferencing.
And then lastly, go to b in memory, like over there, put the tmp value there.
中文字幕
So whereas ampersand in our previous example means,
tell me what the address is of a variable, star is the opposite.
中文字幕
When you have an address, it says, go to that address.
Follow the treasure map, X marks the spot at that location in memory,
中文字幕
and get at its value.
So what is the net effect here?
中文字幕
If I actually now open up not this example, but swap.c--
spoiler, this one is going to actually work.
中文字幕
If I open up swap.c, we're going to see now the following instead.
The code is almost the same, except that I pasted it
中文字幕
in this new green version of the function.
And notice here, this had a change.
中文字幕
Why am I typing in %x now and %y instead of just x and y?
address [INAUDIBLE] functions [INAUDIBLE]..
中文字幕
Exactly.
The swap function now, the new improved version
中文字幕
is expected two addresses-- stars.
Each star, a.k.a. pointers, not just values.
中文字幕
So this means I know x and y are actually integers from week 1.
Now I need the address of x and the address of y
中文字幕
so that swap can follow those treasure maps,
so to speak, and go to those addresses.
中文字幕
So now, when I run this program, this is more like the metaphor with Kelly
where I told her where the milk and OJ were.
中文字幕
Now swap and go to those locations as follows. make swap.
Let me go ahead and then do ./swap, Enter--
中文字幕
ah!
Now it seems to be working.
中文字幕
And we can see as much even with the debugger.
Even though it doesn't seem to be buggy, I can still use debug50
中文字幕
to see and understand my program, if not obvious-- oh,
I still need a breakpoint.
中文字幕
Let's set a breakpoint as before.
Let's rerun debug50.
中文字幕
The right-hand panel will open automatically for me.
And let's go ahead and see, if I start stepping over this,
中文字幕
now I see that x is 1, y is 2, printf prints as much on the screen.
Now I'm going to go ahead and step into swap,
中文字幕
and now notice, it's a little weird-looking,
because now a is an address and b is an address,
中文字幕
but tmp is still an int with a garbage value, but I can fix that.
Now tmp is 1, but notice, a and b's values are not changing,
中文字幕
but what is clearly changing per the code?
So notice, this is weird and cryptic.
中文字幕
a is this 0x value.
That's a big hexadecimal address, like that is where in memory a is.
中文字幕
But you know what?
If I click the little triangle, I can kind of follow that pointer
中文字幕
and go to it.
The debugger is smart like that.
中文字幕
So *a, go to a is 2; and *b at the moment is 2, but if I keep going,
now I've done a switcheroo, and you can see that these values have changed.
中文字幕
And again, we don't care what these addresses are,
I don't care what the actual addresses are.
中文字幕
I do care that it gives me this functionality, because now when
I return up here in print, now the values have indeed
中文字幕
changed as I expected this whole time.
All right.
中文字幕
That was complex, but hopefully clear as to why it now works even though we've
made this code look more cryptic.
中文字幕
If not, any questions are welcome.
Yeah?
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: Is that from the spot where [INAUDIBLE]
Uh huh.
中文字幕
the star [INAUDIBLE] pointers?
Good question.
中文字幕
Do we really need to have these ampersands here because we already
have the stars here?
中文字幕
Short answer, yes, for symmetry.
This is telling the function what to expect on the way in;
中文字幕
this is what's telling the computer actually what to send in.
So what are the actual inputs to that function?
中文字幕
It has to be symmetric.
Yeah?
中文字幕
value is swapping addresses.
We are swapping what is at the addresses.
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: So what if you change the address of [INAUDIBLE]
OK.
中文字幕
AUDIENCE: And would we swap the addresses saying 2 is at 200 and 1
is at [INAUDIBLE] that could change.
中文字幕
Short answer, you cannot for the following reason.
So technically, when you do %x and %y, these are converted to the address
中文字幕
of x, the address of y.
Technically swap is getting copies of something, C has not changed.
中文字幕
But C is now getting copies of the address
of x, copies of the address of y, calling them a and b.
中文字幕
So sure, you could swap the addresses, but for the same reasons as before,
it's going to have no fundamental effect.
中文字幕
The difference here is because I'm passing in a map, so to speak,
to x and y, their addresses.
中文字幕
And again, an address is like--
we are at 45 Quincy Street I think right now--
中文字幕
Cambridge, Massachusetts 02138, USA.
That uniquely identifies the building.
中文字幕
These 0x hexadecimal numbers uniquely identify locations in memory.
So this is like saying now, get me the address of x, get me the address of y,
中文字幕
and I'm technically passing in copies of those addresses, but it doesn't matter,
because now with the star notation, I'm saying go to those addresses
中文字幕
and swap who is physically in this building and some other.
All right.
中文字幕
So let's just put this now into the context of what else
your computer actually has just that you've
中文字幕
seen some nomenclature around this computer's memory.
So this is the chip with a grid laid out on top of it
中文字幕
just to communicate that there's bytes here, and we could number them.
But let's think about this now more abstractly,
中文字幕
and let me just reveal that it turns out that the computer treats
different bytes, different squares in different ways just by convention.
中文字幕
It turns out that in your computer's memory--
and this is all just an artist's representation--
中文字幕
at the top of that chip of memory, so to speak,
is the so-called text of your program.
中文字幕
This is a fancy and non-obvious way of saying
the 0's and 1's that your code have has been compiled into.
中文字幕
The text of a program is the code you wrote in binary,
that's where it's loaded from memory.
中文字幕
So in macOS and Windows, you double-click an icon,
that program is loaded into memory I said last week.
中文字幕
It's literally loaded into the top of your computer's memory conceptually.
What else?
中文字幕
Well the heap is the fancy name given to the chunk of memory in which memory
is coming from when you call malloc.
中文字幕
So when I called malloc earlier to get a bunch of space for some characters,
it was just coming from this big open area called the heap.
中文字幕
And that's what get_string is using and other functions as well.
Well it turns out that the reason for the problem we just ran into
中文字幕
is because the bottom part of memory is what's called the stack.
The stack is the area of memory that functions use when they are called.
中文字幕
And this is actually relevant to that very simple noswap example as follows.
If we now assume that anytime you call a function, the memory it uses
中文字幕
comes from the bottom of that big block of memory,
where you can draw that, for instance, here on the screen,
中文字幕
because it turns out that anytime you call a function, that function gets
a slice of its own memory.
中文字幕
So for instance, main is always the first program a function calls,
and so it gets the first slice of memory at the bottom of the screen here.
中文字幕
And so if main had two variables x and y, that's like saying,
OK, give me a chunk of memory called x and put the value 1 in it;
中文字幕
give me another chunk of memory, call it y, put a value in it here.
But remember, from the first noswap example, the swap function was called.
中文字幕
This is a stack in the literal sense.
You go into a dining hall, a cafeteria, one tray for food, goes on another,
中文字幕
goes on another, goes on another so that the humans can take it
and put food and plates on it.
中文字幕
Well similarly in this model, when you call a function,
it gets its own slice of memory, but literally above, conceptually,
中文字幕
the existing frame on the stack.
So this is the swap function's own chunk of memory,
中文字幕
and it, too, gets some space.
It gets some space for a variable called a.
中文字幕
It gets some space for a variable called b.
And guess what goes inside those of that first example?
中文字幕
A copy of x and a copy of y.
And you know what?
中文字幕
It had a temp variable, so that's got to have some space here.
So I'll call this tmp.
中文字幕
And recall that I set tmp equal to a, so that got 1.
And then what happened?
中文字幕
Well then I did what--
what did I?
中文字幕
Let me get this right.
We had a gets b.
中文字幕
So what happened there?
So in this example here, a gets the value b, so that changed.
中文字幕
And then what happens here, b got the value of 10, so that changed.
So swap was working in the sense that it was swapping values,
中文字幕
but the problem is, when a function returns, this chunk of memory that it
was previously using gets reclaimed so that someone else can now use it,
中文字幕
another function.
So we did all that hard work and no swap, and we did it correctly,
中文字幕
we just did it in the wrong place.
So by contrast, this next example that we did, which was swap.c,
中文字幕
just treated the memory a little bit differently.
Main this time still had two variables called x, and this was a 1,
中文字幕
and then another one called y, and this was a 2.
And then one swap was called this time, it again
中文字幕
had a variable called a and a variable called
b, but what was stored in a and b?
中文字幕
Well now they're addresses.
And I don't know what it is, but let me just arbitrarily say that this
中文字幕
is location 100, this is location--
let's say 104.
中文字幕
But it could be anything, we just don't care at this point,
it would have 0x technically if the computer were showing us.
中文字幕
What's going in a here is 100, what's going in b here is 104.
And those are the addresses of x and y, and the code
中文字幕
we had using all of those new stars was saying,
go to address 100 and store whatever is at address 100 in tmp.
中文字幕
Then go to the address that's in b, or 104,
and store that at the location int *a, whatever is there.
中文字幕
Then it was saying, go get that 10th value, by the way,
and go ahead and put that here, so that now we did
中文字幕
different work in a different place.
So now when swap is done running, it doesn't
中文字幕
matter if its memory disappears because it has now mutated or changed
the other memory.
中文字幕
That it was passed in just like Kelly changed or mutated the cups
I actually pointed her at rather than copies thereof.
中文字幕
Now as an aside, there's other chunks of memory that are actually used.
If you have global variables in a program,
中文字幕
turns out that in between the text and the heap
memory are your global variables, if they're initialized with values
中文字幕
or they're not initialized with values, as would happen with the equal sign,
but we don't care too much about that for today's purposes.
中文字幕
And if you've ever heard of environment variables, which
we will when we get to web programming, they, too,
中文字幕
are stored elsewhere in memory.
But the most interesting chunks of memory
中文字幕
are stack and heap, as in this case here.
But unfortunately it's so easy for things to go awry--
中文字幕
I mean, some of you experienced segmentation faults already,
and let's consider why that might happen.
中文字幕
So here's a contrived example of code that is by design buggy,
but let's just talk it through in English what these lines are doing.
中文字幕
This line here, int *x, is saying, hey, computer,
give me a variable that will store the address of an integer.
中文字幕
So give me a pointer to an int is the more casual way of saying it.
Hey computer, give me another variable that's
中文字幕
going to store the address of an int and call it y.
So x and y, that's it.
中文字幕
This line is new-ish.
Hey computer, allocate enough space that will fit an int.
中文字幕
So sizeof int is the new syntax we saw earlier for just figuring out
how many bytes is an int.
中文字幕
Odds are this is going to come back as 4 or 32 bits in most computers.
So this just says, hey browser, give me 4 bytes of memory
中文字幕
and store that in this location.
Or rather, store that in this variable, store that this variable.
中文字幕
So maybe it's going to say, OK, here's four bytes at location 100,
or here's four bytes at location 900.
中文字幕
Or wherever, we don't care, we're just remembering that address in x.
*x says, go to that address--
中文字幕
100 or 900, whatever it is, put the number 42 there.
This next line says, go to the address in y and put the unlucky number-- hint,
中文字幕
hint--
13 there.
中文字幕
Well what is the address in y?
I haven't allocated it yet.
中文字幕
What's the address in x?
It's wherever malloc told me to use space.
中文字幕
That's safe, that was like 100, 900, whatever the value was,
but did I allocate space for y?
中文字幕
So what kind of value does it contain, so to speak?
A garbage value.
中文字幕
Maybe it's 0, maybe it's like 32,000-- we don't know,
because if you don't specify the value, it
中文字幕
is not safe to trust it or do anything with it.
This is going to give me probably one of those segmentation faults.
中文字幕
And indeed, if I run a program like this,
I'm quite likely going to see exactly that kind of problem.
中文字幕
It's perhaps better, though, to see this in a way that
will paint a more memorable picture, and for that, thought we'd take--
中文字幕
in our 10 minutes remaining, use a few of these minutes
to take a look at something our friends at Stanford
中文字幕
put together with a bit of claymation.
It's about three minutes long, well worth it
中文字幕
to paint a picture of exactly what goes wrong
when you don't use memory correctly.
中文字幕
If you could dim the lights.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
中文字幕
[MUSIC PLAYING]
- Hey, Binky.
中文字幕
Wake up!
It's time for pointer fun!
中文字幕
- What's that?
Learn about pointers?
中文字幕
Oh goody!
- Well to get started, I guess we're going to need a couple of pointers.
中文字幕
- OK.
This code allocates two pointers which can point to integers.
中文字幕
- OK.
Well I see the two pointers, but they don't seem to be pointing to anything.
中文字幕
- That's right.
Initially pointers don't point to anything.
中文字幕
The things they point to are called pointees,
and setting them up to a separate step.
中文字幕
- Oh right, right.
I knew that.
中文字幕
The pointees are separate.
So how do you allocate a pointee?
中文字幕
- OK.
Well this code allocates a new integer pointee,
中文字幕
and this part sets x to point to it.
- Hey, that looks better.
中文字幕
So make it do something.
- OK.
中文字幕
How do you reference the pointer x to store the number 42 into its pointee?
For this trick, I'll need my magic wand of dereferencing.
中文字幕
- Your magic wand of dereferencing?
That-- that's great.
中文字幕
- This is what the code looks like.
I'll just set up the number and--
中文字幕
[POP]
- Hey look!
中文字幕
There it goes.
So doing a dereference on x follows the arrow to access its pointee.
中文字幕
In this case, to store 42 in there.
Hey, try using it to store the number 13 through the other pointer, y.
中文字幕
- OK.
I'll just go over here to y and get the number 13 set up,
中文字幕
and then take the wand of dereferencing and just--
[BUZZING] whoa!
中文字幕
- Oh hey, that didn't work.
Say, Binky, I don't think dereferencing y is a good idea,
中文字幕
cause setting up the pointee is a separate step
and I don't think we ever did it.
中文字幕
- Mmm, good point.
- Yeah.
中文字幕
We allocated the pointer y, but we never set it to point to a pointee.
- Mmm, very observant.
中文字幕
- Hey, you're looking good there, Binky.
Can you fix it so that y points to the same pointee as x?
中文字幕
- Sure.
I'll use my magic wand of pointer assignment.
中文字幕
- Is that going to be a problem like before?
- No, this doesn't touch the pointees.
中文字幕
It just changes one pointer to point to the same thing as another.
- Oh, I see.
中文字幕
Now y points to the same place as x.
So wait, now y is fixed.
中文字幕
It has a pointee.
So you can try the wand of dereferencing again to send the 13 over.
中文字幕
- OK.
Here goes.
中文字幕
- Hey, look at that.
Now dereferencing works on y.
中文字幕
And because the pointers are sharing that one pointee, they both see the 13.
- Yeah, sharing, whatever.
中文字幕
So we going to switch places now?
- Oh look, we're out of time.
中文字幕
- But--
[END PLAYBACK]
中文字幕
All right.
So hopefully that puts a little more visual behind some of these ideas,
中文字幕
but let's now contextualize this in a domain that's perhaps
more familiar in a couple of ways.
中文字幕
So one, some of you might already know, especially
if you've had prior programming experience, of a very popular website
中文字幕
called Stack Overflow where lots of programmers
post questions and hopefully answers to common technical problems.
中文字幕
If you ever wondered why it's called Stack Overflow,
it turns out it reduces to this picture here.
中文字幕
This was not a mistake that I drew one arrow from the heap pointing down,
and one arrow from the stack growing up.
中文字幕
As you malloc, malloc, malloc more and more space,
starts up here, so to speak, and you just get more and more space
中文字幕
that's going this direction.
But the more functions you call-- function after function
中文字幕
after function after a function, each of them
gets its own slice or frame of memory, that, too, is growing up.
中文字幕
So this feels like a pretty bad design, but honestly, it's not really avoidable
because if you have a finite amount of memory,
中文字幕
you can't avoid each other forever.
And so there's this fundamental risk of overflowing the stack,
中文字幕
or even overflowing the heap in the reverse direction.
So Stack Overflow is an allusion to, for instance, calling too
中文字幕
many-- many, many, many, many, many, many, many, many functions,
so many so that it overlaps other chunks or segments of memory,
中文字幕
thereby inducing a segmentation fault, and buffer heap overflow
is in the reverse direction, and these are more
中文字幕
generally known as buffer overflows, and we'll see more of these in the weeks
to come.
中文字幕
But now that we have the ability to discuss pointers,
let's introduce one final feature and then a familiar face.
中文字幕
So it turns out that you can actually come up with your own custom variables
kind of like we did with string, but even more sophisticated than that.
中文字幕
For instance, if I wanted to implement a program that
involves multiple students, I might do something like this.
中文字幕
Ask the user what is the enrollment in a class, then go ahead
and give myself an array of strings, a.k.a.
中文字幕
char*s today of that size, and then I could also have another array of dorms.
And I could have two arrays containing one for the students' names,
中文字幕
one for the students' dorms, and I can keep track of other things.
Another array for emails, another array for phone numbers--
中文字幕
but this gets messy quickly, because you can imagine,
if I need names and dorms and emails and phones,
中文字幕
that starts to become a lot of copy-paste.
And I just have this design where I have lots and lots of arrays
中文字幕
where each bracket location-- like bracket 0, bracket 1
presumably refers to the same student across all of these arrays, like mmm!
中文字幕
Messy, messy, messy design.
So with a wave of my hand, let me actually
中文字幕
fix that immediate problem out of the gate by introducing a new feature.
I can invent my own data types.
中文字幕
Let me just go ahead and declare an array
called students with this many students, but of data type student.
中文字幕
C comes with float, bool, char, int, not string, and definitely not student.
So you can make your own custom data types,
中文字幕
and you can put them in your own header files, which we've not done either.
But I can look, and you'll see more of this in the next problem set.
中文字幕
So not to worry if this feels quite brief,
it's just meant to be a teaser here.
中文字幕
And struct.h is how you declare or define your own type.
The keyword is literally typedef struct for structure, or data structure
中文字幕
to be more complete.
The name of the data structure comes at the end after some curly braces.
中文字幕
And then inside the curly braces you just specify,
well what do you want a student to have?
中文字幕
I want them to have a name, a dorm, maybe a phone number, maybe
an email address, anything I want.
中文字幕
I can just add here.
So that now in my actual code, I can have an array of actual students,
中文字幕
and I can just access them with this new notation like this.
You know that you can index into an array with bracket notation.
中文字幕
What you didn't know until now, perhaps, is that if at that location
is a structure, a.k.a.
中文字幕
struct, you can get at the name, the dorm, or the phone, or the email,
or anything else there just by using a dot-notation, which is
中文字幕
our last piece of new syntax for today.
Everything else is the same.
中文字幕
I can write a program that says so and so is in such and such a dorm
by just saying get the i-th student's name and the i-th student's dorm.
中文字幕
And I can be even fancier, and if I don't want to just print those values,
I can even, now, that I see no understand pointers--
中文字幕
or I've seen pointers and we'll soon understand them
by way of problem sets and practice, I can actually do this.
中文字幕
This is just a little sneak preview of a line of code
that uses a new function called fopen.
中文字幕
fopen this file open, and it takes in the name of the file to open.
You might know of CSV files, they're like simple spreadsheets,
中文字幕
comma separated values.
And quote-unquote "w" means write.
中文字幕
So this says open the file called students.csv in write mode,
so I can write to this file.
中文字幕
Because in this example, as you'll see in the days to come,
I want to write out to a file.
中文字幕
But it turns out to use files, I need to know what a pointer is,
and it's a little weird that it's all caps,
中文字幕
but there is a data type in C called "file," and it's a pointer.
So long story short, what you're going to see in the next problem set
中文字幕
as we explore the world of forensics is the ability
using pointers and a few new functions to open files and get back
中文字幕
the address of that file in memory so that you can go to that address,
change the contents of a file, and save it back out.
中文字幕
All of us take for granted these days that you can go to File, Open and File,
Save, but what's actually happening, pointers are involved,
中文字幕
stuff's getting loaded into memory, and the computer
is dereferencing or going to those addresses
中文字幕
and changing what's at those locations in memory.
Now why might you want to do this?
中文字幕
Well here, of course, is Zamila-- you might
recall from some of the problem sets and the walkthroughs.
中文字幕
Turns out we could try to enhance this picture of her by zooming in,
and here's about as much fidelity as it is in her eyes.
中文字幕
Like I do not see the glint of any criminal's logo
on his or her jacket in the glint of Zamila's eyes.
中文字幕
If you zoom in on an image, and an image, recall, from week 0
is just a grid of pixels or dots, that's all you get.
中文字幕
And you can maybe smooth it out a little bit or clean up the colors,
but you can't just "enhance," quote-unquote,
中文字幕
and see more of the glint in Zamila's eye,
because an image at the end of the day is just a bitmap, a map--
中文字幕
top-down, left-right-- of pixels.
For instance, here's a smiley face.
中文字幕
If you kind of take a look back and you can kind of see a black smiley
face against a white backdrop.
中文字幕
And if we just decide as humans, let's represent white dots
with 1's and black dots with 0's, this might be what's in the file,
中文字幕
this is what the human sees.
So if we have the ability to open that from a file, store it in memory,
中文字幕
and then using pointers go to those locations in memory,
we can even change the smiley face to an unhappy face, for instance, or color it
中文字幕
or do any number of things to it.
Now at quick glance, there's a lot going on in files,
中文字幕
because what a file is is a set of conventions that humans decided
on where humans years ago just decided in a bitmap file,
中文字幕
BMP file-- so an older but still popular file format for images, humans
just decided that, like, we're going to put a bunch of special values
中文字幕
at the first bytes of the file, then some more
special values than the actual RGB pixels in the rest of the file.
中文字幕
So this is meant to look cryptic at first glance,
and the next homework assignment will walk you through this,
中文字幕
but all it is is a convention of what the 0's and 1's mean
in these different locations.
中文字幕
And indeed, the challenge ahead is going to be to do a number of things.
One is to first and foremost figure out--
中文字幕
who done it?
A sort of murder mystery in which there's a clue hidden in an image,
中文字幕
but an image that's a little noisy and you're
going to have to figure out what secret messages in the image
中文字幕
by loading that image in, tweaking it, putting a sort of red filter
on top of it and seeing the secret message, but all digitally; two,
中文字幕
actually resizing images and taking this many pixels in this big
of a smiley face or something else and making it bigger,
中文字幕
or if more comfortable, making it even smaller
and figuring out how to make that workout;
中文字幕
and then lastly, we've been taking some photographs of all CS50 staff
in Cambridge and New Haven.
中文字幕
Unfortunately we accidentally corrupted or lost the memory card,
but we made a forensic image of it, a copy of all of the 0's and 1's with all
中文字幕
of the staff photos, and we're going to need
you to write code that actually recovers all of the JPEGs
中文字幕
or photographs from that digital card by opening a file,
reading in those 0's and 1's, understanding what they are
中文字幕
and where they are, and just writing them
back out to disk using functions we'll introduce you to in the problem
中文字幕
set itself.
But of course, all of this takes for granted that we can do this,
中文字幕
and you can only do so much.
And indeed, this week is as much about solving those problems
中文字幕
as it is realizing the limitations of computers,
and so we thought we'd end with the final few seconds of this very
中文字幕
real example from Futurama.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
中文字幕
- Magnify that death sphere.
Why is it still blurry?
中文字幕
- That's all the resolution we have.
Making it bigger doesn't make it clearer.
中文字幕
- It does on CSI Miami.
- Ugh.
中文字幕
And that's it for CS50, we'll see you next time.